<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The differences of the ages of mans life together with the originall causes, progresse, and end thereof. Written by the learned Henrie Cuffe, sometime fellow of Merton College in Oxford. Ann. Dom. 1600.</title>
            <author>Cuff, Henry, 1563-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857154</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857154</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22836</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22836)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The differences of the ages of mans life together with the originall causes, progresse, and end thereof. Written by the learned Henrie Cuffe, sometime fellow of Merton College in Oxford. Ann. Dom. 1600.</title>
                  <author>Cuff, Henry, 1563-1601.</author>
                  <author>R. M., fl. 1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 128, 131-135, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Arnold Hatfield for Martin Clearke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: R.M.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mortality --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DIFFERENCES OF THE AGES OF MANS Life: <hi>Together with the Originall cauſes, Progreſſe, and End thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by the learned HENRIE CVFFE, ſometime Fellow of <hi>Merton</hi> College in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1600.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Arnold</hi> Hatfield for <hi>Martin Clearke.</hi> 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE</hi> and Noble Lord, <hi>ROBERT</hi> Lord Willughby, Beake, <hi>and</hi> Eresby, <hi>in earth the ground, and in heauen the</hi> accompliſhment of all <hi>true happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My very good Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe (not vnlike vnto bank-rupt-debters) pay what I owe with another mans purſe. For
<pb facs="tcp:22836:3"/>which, notwithſtanding I could plead preſcription from beyond the memorie of man, and deduce preſidents for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe aboue the low flats of neceſsitie: The greateſt doe it; why not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt? For <hi>the actions of ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours be rules of action vnto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, &amp; virum magnum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui eſt penè ſapere,</hi> as the world goeth: yet this I dare profeſſe vnto your Honour, the payment is in good and lawfull money, as good as any that goeth current with Merchants; and if the triall bee true, by touch or teste, farre beyond the alloy of ordinarie mintage. A coyner it had, whom Fame hath reported (for my ſelfe did neuer, <hi>de facie,</hi> knowe him) as skilfull a Maſter in this trade,
<pb facs="tcp:22836:3"/>as our ſhoppes haue brought foorth anie. Who though hee verified that ancient by-word, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet hath he waſhed off from the walles of Lycoeum, that blacke aſperſion of Petronius; <hi>Ego arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tror adoleſcentulos in ſcholis ſtultiſsimos fieri, quia nihil eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quae in vſu habemus, aut audiunt, aut vident.</hi> The worke carrieth both parts of perfection: to Delight, and giue Profit. To Delight the affection with pleaſing varietie, and indow the minde with excellent formes: which like the two handmaids of Queene <hi>Heſter,</hi> ſhould ſuſtaine euery paſſage of learning, though it come not to the preſence of royall <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſhueroſh.</hi> To Profit, by the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:22836:4"/>diſcuſſed and cleered, which is, in part, the knowledge of our ſelues, that which the Poet ſayd, <hi>Came from Heauen,</hi> a good meanes to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuate that, which the Prophet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; <hi>Teach me O Lord to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my daies, that I may applie my heart vnto wiſedome.</hi> To <hi>pleaſe</hi> in <hi>profit,</hi> which it ſelfe is <hi>Content;</hi> and alſo in the maner wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is caried verie <hi>perſpicuous,</hi> and in good <hi>method,</hi> for which cauſe I haue not added anie marginall dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to ſtand, as <hi>Mercuries ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> in high-waies of old, pointing the finger vnto conſequents. It came vnto my hands, <hi>vt è naufragio ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula,</hi> and I return it to your Lordſhip as Lord of the ſoile whereon it was
<pb facs="tcp:22836:4"/>caſt. For vnto your Honor I owe my ſelfe, both in reſpect of priuate ſeruice, as alſo of that right-woorthy houſe, into which by mariage your Honor is inſerted, whereto I ſtande obliged in my beſt indeuours. You haue it whole and intire, as it came vnto my hands, without anie purloining or imbeaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, a ſincere tranſcript from the firſt originall, which I am informed was his own; I durſt not aduenture, though happely I could, to adde anie thing at all vnto that table, in which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi> penſill had beene. Thus cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the continuance of your Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reſpect, and acceptance of my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred dutie by proxey, vntill my owne meanes doe inable my ſufficiencie, (which hitherto hath beene nipped in
<pb facs="tcp:22836:5"/>the budde by the froſts of the night, or withered in the blade for want of moiſture) I thrice humblie take my leaue, and reſt your Honors</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>in all ſeruices,</hi> R. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:6"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He learned <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclite</hi> no leſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legant than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigmaticall, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other his quaint ſpeeches, hath this ſaying of ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance and obſeruation: That the greedy mettall mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, in their too eager ſearch for the meaſured worlds wealth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long toile and trouble, finde
<pb facs="tcp:22836:7"/>
               <hi>paruum in magno,</hi> a little pure ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in a great deale of vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable earth. Contrarily it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the inquiſition and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute of <hi>learning,</hi> where we often finde with a little abſtractiue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, <hi>magnum in paruo,</hi> much matter in few words, euery ſhort golden ſentence and particle thereof containing incredible ſtore of moſt pure ſubſtance. For as the cunning <hi>Coſmographers,</hi> draw the whole compaſſe of the wide <hi>World,</hi> into the narrow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of a ſmall <hi>Mappe;</hi> ſo haue our learned <hi>Artiſts</hi> contracted the vnconceiueable amplitude of the <hi>Liberall Sciences,</hi> into volumes of ſmall quantity. But as gold,
<pb facs="tcp:22836:7"/>the pureſt of all mettals, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer couched in a little compaſſe, is many times beaten out into a maruellous amplitude; ſo the ſhort <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> of <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> in the circuit of a ſmall period, comprehend ſubſtance ſufficient to fill whole volumes. Which truth is confirmed, or rather ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by the preſent matter we intreat of, whereby, as <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> finding the print of <hi>Hercules</hi> his foote geſſed thereby at the proportion of his whole body; ſo we by the view of this ſo little and neglected a peece of <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie,</hi> may gather what we are to thinke of the whole body (that I may ſo ſpeake) of learning.
<pb facs="tcp:22836:8"/>Which I obſerue the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſee many ſhallow headed artificers oftentimes condemne vs of folly, that ſpend our whole <hi>Life</hi> in the ſtudy of good <hi>Letters,</hi> and yet, (ſuch is our groſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit) we neuer come to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite perfection of <hi>Knowledge.</hi> As if our <hi>Artes</hi> were like the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicall ſciences of baſe Prenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that may be throughly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the compaſſe of ſeauen yeeres. It was well ſaid of one, <hi>Ars longa, vita breuis,</hi> we haue a great taske, and a ſhort time. I haue read of ſome who in the compaſſe of three yeeres haue ſailed about the world, but I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet heard of any who in the
<pb facs="tcp:22836:8"/>whole courſe of his life, how la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boriouſly ſo euer paſſed ouer, was able to compaſſe the whole <hi>circle</hi> of <hi>Sciences.</hi> And therefore <hi>Theophraſtes</hi> a learned <hi>Philoſopher</hi> lying on his death bed, accuſed <hi>Nature</hi> of vnkindneſſe or rather want of diſcretion, that ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately doth beſtow the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable benefit of long life vpon brute beaſtes and ſenſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that can neither acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo high a fauour, nor by their length of daies benefit themſelues and others; but man that might in time reſtore decai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nature by perfecting the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect artes, hath his induring but as a moment: implying that
<pb facs="tcp:22836:9"/>the whole courſe of a mans life, was not time ſufficient to worke perfection in. And therefore, well ſaid <hi>Sigiſmunde</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> to a <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> whom for an excellent <hi>Stratagem</hi> againſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy he had knighted not long before, when at an aſſembly of his <hi>Peeres</hi> and <hi>Counſellers,</hi> the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> doubted to whether compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he might with greateſt credit ioyne himſelfe, <hi>Is it doubtfull,</hi> ſaid the Emperour, <hi>whether learning or military experience is more honorable? I can in one day make a thouſand good ſouldiers; but I am not able in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres to make one tolerable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</hi> So that it is no maruell though <hi>Socrates,</hi> after his long
<pb facs="tcp:22836:9"/>time of life, yet on his death bed confeſſed he had many things to learne. And me thinketh theſe nimble witted tradeſmen, doe not ſo much magnifie their owne quicke conceit, as publiſh the facility of their ſciences. For as <hi>Apelles</hi> ſaid well vnto a <hi>Painter</hi> that bragged of his ſpeedy work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, when ſhewing his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture he ſaid, <hi>This I drew euen now: Surely,</hi> ſaid <hi>Apelles, though thou hadſt ſaied nothing, yet ſhould I eaſily haue gueſſed by the workemanſhip that it was done in haſte.</hi> So may we well ſay to theſe quicke-witted me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicall tradeſmen, a man that hath but a little inſight into their trade may well thinke their
<pb facs="tcp:22836:10"/>craftes are ſoone learned: and I rather maruell, (as <hi>Apelles</hi> ſaid) that they learned no more in the ſame quantitie and length of time. But it fareth with their groſſe phantaſie as it doth with our eie-ſight in an vnequall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the obiect: for as being far off we conceiue of the vnmeaſurable greatneſſe of the moſt huge hilles to bee but as a point: ſo the infinite excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the heauenly <hi>Artes</hi> being too farre remooued from their groſſe, or rather narrow capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, come into their conceite as things of leſſe moment: which if their dimme or rather weake eie ſight were able to beholde in
<pb facs="tcp:22836:10"/>their diuine nature, they would ſoone confeſſe their ſurpasſing excellency, and exceeeding dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty. But to leaue them to their pleaſing opinions, and to come to our purpoſe, which is, in briefe to handle the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>Ages</hi> of <hi>Mans life,</hi> as alſo the <hi>cauſes</hi> thereof, together with the incident <hi>qualities</hi> to euery of them, which being in ſome ſort auaileable to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of our ſelues, the higheſt point of knowledge which can be attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, by the iudgement of the wiſe <hi>Apollo,</hi> as alſo either al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together omitted or very ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled by others, I hope my ſmall paines and leſſe ability
<pb facs="tcp:22836:11"/>ſhall be accepted in good worth and accounted of, rather accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the good intent of the author, than the worthineſſe of the worke. In which hope of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation for my good indeuors, and fauourable pardon of my manifold errors, I come without any longer Preface to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Treatiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:11"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:22836:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22836:12"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE DIFFERENCES</hi> of the Ages of mans <hi>Life:</hi> Together with the originall cauſes, <hi>progreſſe, and end</hi> thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AN the <hi>Epitome</hi> of the whole <hi>world, Lord</hi> of the <hi>creatures,</hi> in regard of that perfect analogie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance betweene him &amp; the great worlds frame, is not vnfitly by the Learned, both <hi>Diuines</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> termed, The <hi>Leſſer world:</hi> for there is nothing in the vaſte compaſſe of this vniuerſall circumference, whoſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and liuely repreſentation we haue not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22836:13"/>ſummarily compriſed in man, as in a moſt perfect compendium and abridgement. For as the <hi>firſt-moued-ſphere</hi> carieth with its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſubiect inferiour <hi>circles;</hi> ſo the ſeruile vnderfaculties, as the <hi>ſenſuall deſire</hi> &amp; <hi>appetite,</hi> are by <hi>nature</hi> ſubdued to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and guidance of the more principall and miſtris-power of the ſoule, which wee call <hi>reaſon.</hi> And as in the middeſt of heauen there is ſituated the <hi>Sunne</hi> that enlightneth all things with his raies, and cheriſheth the world, and the things therein contained with his life-keeping <hi>heat:</hi> ſo the heart of man, the fountaine of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>heat,</hi> hath aſſigned to it by <hi>nature,</hi> the middle part of our body for his habitation, from whence proceedeth <hi>life</hi> and <hi>heat,</hi> vnto all the parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, (as it were vnto riuers) whereby they be preſerued and inabled to performe their naturall and proper functions. But not to be infinite in proſecuting the particulars of this well knowen compariſon, as in other things we ſee a perfect proportion, ſo alſo, beſide the <hi>analogie</hi> we may obſerue a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>coexiſtence.</hi> For as the <hi>world</hi> at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was created for <hi>man,</hi> ſo with <hi>man</hi> it ſhall alſo be aboliſhed: for it is an vndeniable principle in <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> that <hi>God and Nature,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:22836:13"/>or rather the <hi>God of Nature neither effectually worketh, nor permiſſiuely ſuffereth any thing, but vnto ſome good end.</hi> For being infinitely wiſe, nay <hi>wiſedome</hi> it ſelfe, how can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine ſo high a point of folly, reſident in his Godhead, as to allow of <hi>vanities,</hi> things ſo hatefull, and ſo abhorring from all medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity of wiſedome? Wherefore man hauing a determinate date of endurance which hee cannot paſſe, the <hi>world</hi> alſo, which is only for mans vſe and ſeruice, muſt of neceſſity haue an end of being. Now becauſe there is (as we ſaid) a mutuall coexiſtence of the world and man, as the world is not but for man, ſo neither is man, but in and by the world. For as in <hi>Nauigation,</hi> thoſe that are in the <hi>ſhippe,</hi> haue reſt and motion with the mouing &amp; ceſſation of the <hi>ſhip,</hi> ſo we that are toſſed in the rough ſea of this <hi>world,</hi> in our voiage vnto <hi>heauen</hi> our ſafeſt hauen, when our veſſell of carriage once periſheth, we alſo periſh together. For as <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſaid truely, that <hi>whatſoeuer hath being, hath of neceſſity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſome place;</hi> ſo from thence ariſeth this neceſſary illation, that when there is once left no place to be in, then ſhall there remaine no longer being. So that intending to ſhew this truth as very pertinent to our purpoſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22836:14"/>viz. <hi>that man hath an appointed time of being, which hee cannot paſſe,</hi> the <hi>Queſtion</hi> of the <hi>worlds eternity</hi> is fitly incident, eſpecially, ſeeing, as is aforeſaid, the world is for mans ſake, and man by meanes of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Now if any man ſhall call into queſtion, the pertinency of this <hi>queſtion,</hi> for his ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and reſolution in that behalfe, let him conſider, how neceſſarily vpon the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of our <hi>temperature</hi> (whence the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ages proceedeth) a finall deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by an vnperceiueable lingring decay of purity in our ſubſtance, doth depend. For as in the violent motion of things <hi>naturall,</hi> we ſee it comes to paſſe, that the <hi>virtue</hi> or <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of mouing, imprinted by the vnnaturall <hi>mouer,</hi> by little and little decaying, at length by continuance of mouing, or rather by the reſiſtance of the bodies about it, is cleane extinguiſhed: So in the naturall proceeding toward the enemie and end of <hi>nature, death</hi> the preſeruing meanes of life (either by the toileſomeneſſe of their neuer-ceaſing opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or by the corruption and mixture of impure moiſture, infecbled and diſabled to the ſufficient performance of their functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, more and more euery day) at length of force yeelds to the oppreſſing violence of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22836:14"/>their reſiſting aduerſaries, not able any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to maintaine their conquering action, ſo that the diſcuſſing of this contronerſie is very homogeneous to the ſeries of this treatiſe. For till there be granted an end of mans life, the mutation of the temperature by decay of nature may well be doubted of, foraſmuch as <hi>a ſucceſſiuc impairing alway importeth a finall diſſolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Firſt therefore touching the continuance of the <hi>world,</hi> whether as it had a <hi>beginning,</hi> ſo it ſhall haue an <hi>end,</hi> or rather whether it euer had <hi>beginning,</hi> or ſhall haue an <hi>end</hi> of being. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> in his booke <hi>de Diuinis nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus,</hi> diſtinguiſheth things that are, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the difference of their indurance; the diſtinction is after this ſort. The whole number of things, how many and diuers ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, may be ſummarily compriſed vnder theſe three ſeuerall heads. There are ſome things, or rather there is one thing <hi>Eternall,</hi> which neither had <hi>beginning</hi> nor ſhall haue <hi>end,</hi> and ſuch is <hi>God</hi> alone, who onely being immutable, ſubiect to none, no not the leaſt alteration, is therefore only from euerlaſting to euerlaſting, for that cauſe termed in holy writ, the <hi>Ancient of daies:</hi> amongſt the old <hi>Egyptians</hi> reſembled to a <hi>decrepit-old-man,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:22836:15"/>and pourtraied like a <hi>youth</hi> in the prime of his flouriſhing yeares: by that firſt <hi>Image</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying his long continuance from before, by the ſecond, his liuelineſſe and immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from all manerdefect and alteration by cancred corrupting time. For as his power is infinite, extended not onely to all things in the world, but euen vnto things which are not: as firſt hee made all things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as his greatneſſe is vnmeaſurable, not limited or bounded by any place or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, and therefore ſaid to haue his <hi>centrum vbique,</hi> from which the <hi>eſſence</hi> of al things is drawen, as <hi>lines,</hi> and where they end and are all conioyned, &amp; his <hi>circumference no where:</hi> finally, as all his attributes are <hi>infinite,</hi> and immeaſurable, ſo is his continuance altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther boundleſſe. Wherefore not to enter at all into this inextricable <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> infinite continuance, let vs proceed vnto the next part of the diſtinction. Beſide <hi>God,</hi> who is onely <hi>Eternall,</hi> there are other things in a middle degree, tearmed by the moderne <hi>Philoſophers, Euiternall,</hi> hauing <hi>beginning</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> the fountaine of <hi>being,</hi> yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>end,</hi> either of <hi>annihilation,</hi> or <hi>corruption;</hi> ſuch are all ſpirituall creatures, <hi>Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Soules</hi> of men. Where notwithſtanding
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22836:15"/>there is a doubt to be anſwered: For in the whole <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> of the <hi>Creation</hi> recorded by <hi>Moſes,</hi> we finde no mention of the making of Angels, nor any word of them till the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Womans</hi> treacherous ſeduction by the <hi>diuel</hi> in the <hi>ſerpent,</hi> ſo that either they were not <hi>created,</hi> and ſo were from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, or elſe, <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Chronicle</hi> is in this point defectiue. But wee may well anſwer, that they had a beginning, ſeeing that <hi>eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is <hi>Gods</hi> peculiar <hi>attribute,</hi> and the ſame, though incluſiuely, expreſſed by <hi>Moſes</hi> in his booke of <hi>beginnings:</hi> for by Heauen is ſignified, not onely the body of heauen, but the things alſo therein contained. Now of the indirect, and incluſiue mention made of theſe admirable creatures, there may this reaſon be giuen: The men of thoſe times being very ſuperſtitious, and giuen vnto I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, (for the <hi>Egyptians</hi> euen at that time worſhipped the <hi>Sunne,</hi> &amp; the <hi>hoſts of heauen</hi>) <hi>Moſes</hi> fearing to giue new occaſion to their falſe <hi>will-worſhip,</hi> of purpoſe refrained from expreſſe mentioning of their names, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in his <hi>hiſtory.</hi> For if theſe bodily vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible creatures, wrung from them ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine worſhip, the <hi>Angels,</hi> by how much more excellent their nature is, would haue ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22836:16"/>much the more added new fewell to their begun fire of ſuperſtition. Secondly, leſt the detractory Nature of corrupted man, ſhould haue aſcribed ſome part of the glory of the worlds creation to thoſe heauenly creatures, the wiſe pen-man of this excellent ſtory, of purpoſe concealed what hee knew either of their <hi>Creation</hi> or <hi>Nature:</hi> ſo that <hi>Moſes</hi> his hiſtory is in this regard not defectiue, howſoeuer giuing no expreſſe notion of the creation of <hi>Angels.</hi> Neither are the <hi>Angels,</hi> though moſt excellent <hi>creatures,</hi> void of beginning, there being but one thing, which one made <hi>all</hi> things, of it ſelfe, <hi>eternall.</hi> The third degree is of thoſe things that had both beginning with <hi>time,</hi> and ſhal haue their end in <hi>time;</hi> ſuch are all bodily creatures as well ſimple as mixt, although touching the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall bodies there be ſome doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Now as concerning the <hi>world,</hi> the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, to which of theſe three kinds, it may and ought to be referred. And I finde three ſeuerall opinions. The firſt is of them that make the <hi>world eternall,</hi> wanting <hi>beginning,</hi> and incapeable of <hi>end.</hi> The ſecond of them that grant both <hi>beginning</hi> and <hi>end of being.</hi> There is a third ſect that parts theſe two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, affirming, that it had a <hi>beginning</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:22836:16"/>and ſhall haue no <hi>end.</hi> But leſt wee ſticke in the words, let vs in one word or two, ſet downe the ſenſe and meaning of the <hi>Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and becauſe that <hi>crror</hi> is the child of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,</hi> diſtinguiſh the things doubtfull, leſt through the equiuocation of the words, by miſtaking, wee come vnto a contrary ſenſe. By the <hi>world</hi> therfore, ſometime is meant the whole compaſſe of things that are, as well ſpirituall as bodily, extended in this ſenſe euen vnto God himſelfe. Secondly it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for all things, only <hi>God</hi> excepted, euen the whole worke of the <hi>Creation,</hi> excluding no creature how excellent ſoeuer, no not the <hi>Angels.</hi> Thirdly it ſignifieth onely the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite of bodily <hi>Creatures,</hi> whether you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret bodily things to be ſuch as haue bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as parts of them, or ſuch as, though in regard of compoſition haue no bodies, yet haue their being onely in creatures bodily, as thoſe things which we call <hi>Accidents.</hi> For the firſt acception it concerneth not our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelfe excludeth <hi>God</hi> from all kinde of <hi>beginning,</hi> and it is a principle both in reaſon, and in religion that <hi>God is from euerlaſting.</hi> In the ſecond ſenſe wee may take it, comprehending all things both ſpirituall and bodily: for euen the <hi>Angels</hi> as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22836:17"/>is before ſaid, had their <hi>beginning</hi> by <hi>creation:</hi> but we rather hold our ſelues vnto the laſt ſignification, as being moſt vſually meant by thoſe that handle this controuerſie. And this alſo according to its threefold conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, hath three ſeuerall acceptions? For firſt it is taken for that <hi>Idaea</hi> &amp; type precon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of the <hi>Maker God,</hi> by which he was ruled and directed in the building thereof. And this is tearmed by <hi>Plato,</hi> the <hi>Ideal</hi> or <hi>exemplary world,</hi> as it were the <hi>copie</hi> which <hi>God</hi> followed in the creation: whereby if he vnderſtand <hi>Gods decree</hi> to create, we may without error entertain it; otherwiſe it is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what harſh: for we are not to imagine that <hi>God</hi> needeth any long premeditate or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiued type of his workes, as our finite artificers do, but as his wiſedome, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is infinite, ſo doth hee, in an vnutterable manner at the ſame moment, deuiſe the manner and performe the worke, and yet, not raſhly, but moſt wiſely, and with great deliberation. For as he ſaid in another ſenſe, ſo may I ſay in this caſe, <hi>One day with God, is as a thouſand yeares, and a thouſand yeares as one day;</hi> length of time adding nothing to his ability and wiſedome, nor fewneſſe of daies, any way detracting from the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22836:17"/>of his workemanſhip. Secondly it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the <hi>vniuerſity</hi> of things contained within the compaſſe and cope of heauen and earth, now really and actually ſubſiſting; and this is called of <hi>Plato,</hi> the <hi>world reall,</hi> as hauing an actuall and externall being in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> not onely in conceit and intention. Thirdly man is called the <hi>leſſer world,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that perfect analogie and ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, betwixt him and this greater world, wherein there is nothing whoſe likeneſſe and reſemblance may not be ſeene in man: and this you may call the <hi>Analogicall world.</hi> Now by the world in our queſtion, we prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally vnderſtand, the frame of all things in heauen and in earth: leſſe principally <hi>Man,</hi> as being but a part thereof. As for the other terme, namely <hi>Eternall,</hi> that alſo hath two acceptions; for things are ſaid to bee <hi>Eternall</hi> two waies: Firſt improperly, that which neuer ſhall haue end, more fitly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Euiternall</hi> or <hi>Immortall.</hi> Properly that is ſaid to be <hi>Eternall</hi> which neither had begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor ſhall haue end, nor as <hi>Boethius</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, any <hi>ſucceſſion.</hi> Now <hi>Eternall,</hi> we take in the more proper and latter ſenſe. So that the <hi>Queſtion</hi> may thus more plainlie be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Whether the heauen and earth, with the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22836:18"/>bodily Creatures therein contained, had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, or ſhall haue an end of being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> But becauſe that part of the opinion which concerneth the worlds eternitie, <hi>a parte ante,</hi> as the <hi>ſchoole-men</hi> ſpeake, that is, its being from euerlaſting, is not ſo directly pertinent vnto our purpoſe, we will with all poſſible breuitie runne ouer the ſpeciall reaſons, and foundations thereof, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe the authors and maintainers thereof from the want of <hi>beginning,</hi> inferre the vncapableneſſe of an <hi>end.</hi> Now the chiefe <hi>Patron</hi> and deſender of this opinion in regard of authoritie, though not of time, was <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who, as I take it, rather affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſingularitie, than for any ſoundneſſe of the matter or ſtrength of argument, tanght it in his <hi>Lycoeum.</hi> For the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> which liued before him, with generall conſent agreed in the contrarie opinion: <hi>Triſmegistus,</hi> who with his learning wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the then barren countrey of <hi>Greece,</hi> as <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> witneſſeth in his firſt booke of <hi>Antiquities, Muſaeus, Orpheus, Linus, Epicharmus, Heſiodus, and Homer,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Poets; Zoroaſtes, Anaxagoras, Meliſſus, Empedocles, Pherecides, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus, Democritus,</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> as <hi>Philo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22836:18"/>Laertius Diogenes, Sulcitius Seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Alexander Aphrodiſienſis, Plutarch, and Tully</hi> witneſſe, which alſo his bookes intituled <hi>Timaeus,</hi> and <hi>Critias,</hi> together with thoſe <hi>De Republica</hi> doe teſtifie. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in a ſelfe-conceit of ſingularity, howſoeuer elſewhere honoring antiquitie, rather liketh in this caſe a new broched opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his owne, contrary to ſo many fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going <hi>Philoſophers:</hi> and therefore <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantes,</hi> a deuout, though idolatrous <hi>Prieſt,</hi> condemned him of arrogancie, and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, not onely becauſe, contrarie to the common receiued opinion of his countrey, continued ſo many ages vngainſaied, hee denied the <hi>pluralitie of Gods,</hi> but alſo, and much more for that he ſtucke not to teach, that the world was from euerlaſting, which all <hi>Greece</hi> confeſſed to haue had beginning in time.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> But to fetch the beginning of this phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall opinion ſomewhat higher: we will beginne with <hi>Democritus,</hi> the archpatron of <hi>fortune,</hi> who will haue the World Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and withall chanceable: But Eternitie and Chance, being (as the learned <hi>Sir Philip</hi> obſerued) things vnſufferable together; If Chanceable, then not Eternall. Againe,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22836:19"/>what is more abſurd then to thinke the World was made by the vntended, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall concourſe of indiuiſible ſubſtances? for whence came theſe ſubſtances? If you ſay they came from <hi>Euerlaſting,</hi> &amp; ſo were Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, can you conceiue ſuch chanceable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects to proceed from ſo certaine &amp; neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſes? Nay rather, if you wil needs main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane the infinitenes of theſe diminitiue bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, grant they had beginning from that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite One that glued the Infinite parts of your <hi>Infinite. All,</hi> together, by his vnmeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome.</hi> For can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine ſuch a perfect <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Stabilitie</hi> to conſiſt in theſe diſioined ſubſtances? <hi>Order</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſtancie</hi> are children onely of <hi>Wiſdome:</hi> &amp; ſooner may we prooue <hi>Darkneſſe</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the <hi>Sunne,</hi> than <hi>Conſtancie</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> from inconſtant <hi>chance,</hi> conſtant in nothing but in <hi>Inconſtancie.</hi> Finally, we muſt either exclude Gods <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent care of the <hi>World</hi> made, or els <hi>Fortune</hi> from making of the <hi>World:</hi> (for the <hi>World</hi> is Gods poſſeſſion, onely by right of <hi>creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) vnleſſe we imagine a <hi>deed of gift</hi> paſſed by <hi>Fortune</hi> at her death: or <hi>Fortune</hi> the true <hi>Owner,</hi> (if the true <hi>Maker</hi>) diſinherited, &amp; by violence driuen out of her dominion by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22836:19"/>
               <hi>God</hi> as an <hi>Vſurper.</hi> But <hi>God</hi> hauing nothing to plead for his title vnto his kingdome, but the right of <hi>creation,</hi> if that plea be improo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, God cannot any longer call the <hi>World</hi> his owne, and therefore without crueltie may caſt off all care of this his ſuppoſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring. For it is onely Gods <hi>Fatherhood</hi> that bindes him vnto his <hi>Prouidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Therefore not to ſtay long in this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Fortune,</hi> let vs now come vnto <hi>Nature,</hi> deified eſpecially by <hi>Strato</hi> a <hi>Naturaliſt:</hi> who fearing to ouerſway God with the weight of this burthen, either in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or gouerning of the <hi>World,</hi> hath gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hm a <hi>Remedie,</hi> or <hi>Otium</hi> as they terme it, thinking it more reaſon that God ſhould haue an exemption from trouble, than Gods <hi>prieſts,</hi> who for his ſake be diſpenſed withall. But let vs ſee, what this <hi>Nature</hi> may bee, ſo highly by <hi>Strato</hi> magnified. There is a <hi>particular Nature,</hi> and there is a <hi>generall</hi> or <hi>vniuerſall Nature.</hi> The particular is that which in euery ſeuerall ſingle <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> miniſtreth <hi>Eſſence</hi> to the whole <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound:</hi> and withall, is <hi>author</hi> of ſuch action, and <hi>motion,</hi> as is agreeable to the ſubiect wherein it is, as the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>fire,</hi> cauſeth the <hi>fires</hi> aſcention, the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>earth,</hi> the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22836:20"/>
               <hi>earths</hi> going downward: and in regard of this <hi>Nature,</hi> we ſay it is <hi>Naturall</hi> to the <hi>fire</hi> to aſcend, to the <hi>earth</hi> to deſcend, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies hauing in them, cuen of themſelues, by their inherent forme a promptneſſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination vnto theſe motions. Now if by the conſpiring of theſe many &amp; manifold <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> this <hi>All,</hi> we now ſpeake of, were made, as if the <hi>Elements,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ethereall</hi> parts ſhould in their <hi>town-houſe</hi> ſet downe the bounds of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ones office; then conſider what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that there muſt needs haue beene, a wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ouerruling power, which made them concur: for their natures being ſo diuers and contrary, would rather haue wrought each others deſtruction, than ſo friendly haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted, to make vp ſo vnexpreſſable an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. For, to grant <hi>knowledge</hi> vnto them whereby to moderate the extremity of their naturall fury, or intendment of ſuch agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were to enter into a bottomleſſe pit of abſurdities, ſeeing that <hi>knowledge</hi> alway pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth <hi>roaſon,</hi> &amp; <hi>reaſon</hi> ſenſe; both which are neuer found, either iointly, or in part, in bodilie ſenſeleſſe creatures. Now touching the <hi>Vninerſall Nature,</hi> which ſome will haue to be nothing, but <hi>an influent virtue, helping &amp; furthering the actions of euery particular na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22836:20"/>body,</hi> others, an <hi>Vniuerſall ouerruling,</hi> and as it were, <hi>an Ideall Nature ſubſiſting.</hi> For as the particular nature of euery particular <hi>body,</hi> cauſeth and mainetaineth the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>actions</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> wherein it is; ſo this generall Nature is the author and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of all <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>bodies:</hi> to which, the ſingle ſeuerall bodies are in ſubiection, by their obedience acknowledging a kinde of ſuperiority, in that nature which we call <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall.</hi> And in the reſpect of this nature, the fire is ſaid, in ſome caſes, to goe downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, by nature, as to hinder the <hi>diſcontinui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of things in the world, and ſo, that <hi>empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> which nature ſo much abhorreth. Now, if by this vniuerſall nature, they vnderſtand a nature of <hi>wiſedome,</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidence,</hi> which with <hi>knowledge</hi> performeth its actions, and ſo of purpoſe, &amp; deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath knit togethet theſe ſo many points to ſuch an excellent <hi>vnitie,</hi> this Nature wee reiect not, but retaine, as that <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> of all things, that by his infinite irreſiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power bath conioined the diſagreeing parts of this viſible world, and of things contrary made a perfect harmony, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in their nature a mutuall reſiſtance; yet ſo, as they hinder not their friendly copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22836:21"/>in the worlds compoſition. In ſum, touching <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Fortune,</hi> they are thus onely (ſaith <hi>Scaliger</hi>) to be interpreted: that <hi>Nature</hi> ſignifies <hi>Gods</hi> ordinary power; and thus, things <hi>extraordinary</hi> may be called <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall: Fortune</hi> his vnreuealed <hi>will,</hi> and thus may wee call things <hi>chanceable</hi> that are beſide <hi>expectation</hi> or beyond <hi>reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Now touching the <hi>Epicure,</hi> who (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith) deriued his opinion from <hi>Democritus,</hi> we will in one word anſwer his reaſon, recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Tully</hi> in his ſecond booke <hi>de Natura Deorum,</hi> and ſo come vnto <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and his <hi>Scholar</hi> the Atheiſt. The <hi>Epicures</hi> reaſon is briefly thus propounded by way of interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: What eies (ſaith he in his ſcoffing impudency) had <hi>Plato,</hi> to behold the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of this ſo great a worke? Or what tooles, and fellow-workemen had <hi>God</hi> to make the <hi>World</hi> withall? The anſwer is, that <hi>Plato</hi> his eie, was the eie of <hi>reaſon,</hi> gathering by neceſſary conſequence, both the being of the Deity, as alſo confuſedly apprehending the infiniteneſſe of <hi>God</hi> his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>wiſdome</hi> ſhinig in the <hi>world,</hi> as in a moſt cleere glaſſe reflecting, in ſome ſort, the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> inuiſible <hi>Nature,</hi> vpon the eies of all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders. Touching abſence of inſtruments
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22836:21"/>and fellow-workemen, whereby the <hi>Epicure</hi> would inferre the impoſſibility to create in <hi>God,</hi> we are not to thinke, that <hi>God, infinite in power,</hi> is tied to the helpe of ſecundary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall cauſes, they being but ſupplies of defects, and helps of wants, in the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe inſufficient agents: and therefore not requiſit, to the eternall infiniteneſſe of <hi>Gods</hi> ability. Nay we may adde further, which is <hi>Gods</hi> priuiledge, <hi>God</hi> of <hi>nothing,</hi> is powerfull enough to make <hi>all</hi> things, much more with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inſtruments. Now a poſſibility of <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> may thus briefly be ſhewn: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the maner of <hi>being</hi> of euery thing, ſo alſo is the order of <hi>working;</hi> but <hi>Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>beginning</hi> dependeth vpon nothing but himſelfe: why then ſhould it be thought impoſſible, that <hi>Gods</hi> action is not tied vnto any matter? And indeed, the reaſon (as far as I can perceiue) why other things require a ſubject whereon to worke, is onely the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of the <hi>Agents,</hi> but <hi>God Al-ſufficient,</hi> and powerfull, who can out of the <hi>rocks</hi> bring <hi>water,</hi> out of <hi>darkeneſſe light,</hi> can alſo (as he hath done) make <hi>all</hi> things of <hi>nothing.</hi> An other reaſon may be this, taken from the difference of the principall <hi>efficients, God, Nature, Arte. Arte,</hi> alway preſuppoſeth a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22836:22"/>thing <hi>really and perfectly ſubſiſting: Nature</hi> onely a <hi>matter</hi> with a <hi>power to be God,</hi> (a farre more powerfull <hi>Agent</hi> then either <hi>Arte</hi> or <hi>Nature</hi>) is able, of that which is <hi>nothing</hi> at all, to make a thing of actuall and reall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence. For, if <hi>Nature</hi> can of a thing in the loweſt degree of being, and next to a not being, make a thing actually ſubſiſting, <hi>God All-ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>infinit in power,</hi> can of <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> create any thing in what degree of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Now touching the Atheiſt, out of <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> his <hi>Philoſophie</hi> he hath drawen this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <hi>Interrogatorie,</hi> which hee propoundeth with ſo vnſauorie ſcorne: If the <hi>world</hi> were not from Euerlaſting, but made by the <hi>God</hi> you talke of, I would know of you, where he liued before the time that hee made the world; how he buſied himſelfe all the time before? for it is an abſurdity, euen among vs, to ſay, he was <hi>idle:</hi> as alſo what he did, if he did not make it from euerlaſting? Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place of his being, and the maner of his worke, I may not vnfitly anſwer, as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>Primitiue Church</hi> did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame demand; <hi>He was in a wood proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fewell for that fire, which ſhould in heltor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch curious priers into matters beyond
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22836:22"/>their reach.</hi> But for his <hi>location,</hi> I may thus more fitly anſwer: that <hi>God</hi> is tied to no <hi>place,</hi> being in all <hi>places</hi> to fill them with his <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> in no <hi>place</hi> to be circumſcribed by the <hi>circumference.</hi> Touching his action we anſwer, that howſoeuer the externall worke, (the after-fruit of his externall working) had no externall ſenſible being, yet was hee not vnoccupied, his very decreeing being an action, and that alſo hauing relation vnto the creatures, which ſhould afterward haue being. The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> (who many times do but trifle in matters of waight) giue vnto this friuolous queſtion, as friuolous an anſwer, ſaying, that God to keepe himſelfe vnoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, ſpent that time in trifling experiments, now making a world on this faſhion, now on that, then by and by diſſoluing his looſe &amp; diſpleaſing worke; at length by many trials, to haue light vpon this <hi>world,</hi> &amp; this <hi>faſhion,</hi> which for his conceiued liking, he eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. But theſe learned <hi>Rabbins,</hi> meant a more ſerious matter then their words beare ſhew of: and that was, that God did not raſhly; nor without great deliberation make the world on this faſhion rather than any other, and that he ſawe he might haue made it many other waies, and ſooner, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22836:23"/>more worlds, but would not: alluding, as I take it, to <hi>Gods</hi> counſell-taking, at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decree, touching the time and maner of the worlds creation, which was the ſum of our firſt giuen anſwer. But more ſoundly and to the purpoſe we anſwer, that the actions of the <hi>Deity</hi> are of two ſorts, <hi>immanent &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall:</hi> or <hi>externall</hi> and <hi>tranſeunt:</hi> the <hi>immanent</hi> actions, are thoſe which bee in the <hi>Deitie</hi> from one <hi>perſon</hi> vnto another, as to loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſuch like: the <hi>tranſeunt</hi> actions are thoſe, that paſſe from the <hi>Godhead</hi> to ſome externall obiect: they may both bee thus illuſtrated. As in the element of <hi>fire</hi> there is a facultie of heating and enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whence proceedeth heat and light vnto the externall neere bodies, and beſide this facultie there is alſo in it a naturall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to go vpward, which when it commeth into <hi>act,</hi> is receiued in no other ſubiect but the <hi>fire</hi> it ſelfe: ſo that, if <hi>fire</hi> could by abſtractiue imagination be conceiued of, as wanting theſe two <hi>tranſeunt</hi> operations, yet could we not iuſtly ſay it had no <hi>action,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it might mooue vpward, which is an immanent and inward action. So, and much more ſo, though we grant that there was no externall worke of the <hi>Godhead,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22836:23"/>the making of the world, yet can there be no neceſſarie illation of <hi>idleneſſe,</hi> ſeeing it might haue, (as indeed it had) actions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent included in the circle of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Againe, thus reaſon theſe blaſphemous Atheiſts againſt the truth: If for mans ſake <hi>God</hi> made the world, and all things therein, how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth it to paſſe, that there are in the world ſo many noiſome creatures, as vipers and ſuch like, which procure rather our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noiance, than ſerue any way for our vſe and benefit? For to ſay they are chanceable, or of a voluntary &amp; ſelfe procreation, is (in our Philoſophy) abſurd, eſpecially, ſeeing we extend <hi>Gods power,</hi> and <hi>prouidence</hi> vnto <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie flies,</hi> and ſuch like creatures. But we may anſwer, firſt that there is nothing ſo cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, which is not ſome way ſeruiceable. Or, if now diſobedient, yet not ſo created, but, for mans rebellion againſt God, permitted or rather directed to arme themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, for whoſe vſe and helpe they were created: like vnto that ſword, which <hi>Hector</hi> gaue <hi>Aiax,</hi> which ſo long as he vſed againſt men his enemies, ſerued for his helpe and defence; but after that he began to vſe it, or rather to abuſe it, to the hurt of hurtleſſe beaſts, it turned into his owne bowels. For
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22836:24"/>vntill the tranſgreſſion <hi>Adam</hi> liued as Lord of the creatures, hauing the now moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and pernicious creatures vnder him in ſubiection. For the diuell, that ſubtle ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer, was not ſo ſimple a ſot, as to make choiſe of the ſerpent to beguile him wth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements, if he had knowen, or but ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted any reſident feare in man of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, by ſome foregoing remembred miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; for that had beene rather to terrifie him from all attention, then any way to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure him to follow his counſell. So that, all things which now are vnto corrupted man moſt cumberſome, as puniſhments of his diſloialty, were by creation ordained for his furtherance. Nor need they wonder, that <hi>Gods</hi> power and knowledge ſhould ſtretch it ſelfe vnto flies and ſuch diminutiue crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as they tearme them: nay it is far more inſenſible, that the eſtate of flies ſhould bee vnknowen vnto him, for that were to bound the infinitneſſe of his knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> But to leaue the profeſſed Atheiſt, who though from <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his ſchoole he ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his noiſome error, yet went farre beyond <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in impiety: For <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (at leaſt in words) confeſted Gods being, an infinitnes, which alſo hee went about to prooue and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22836:24"/>confirme by reaſon, whereas theſe godleſſe Heretikes doe not onely deny both in their works, and by conſequence of words, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhameleſly with direct ſpeeches, not only his <hi>omnipotency,</hi> but euen his very <hi>being:</hi> let vs therefore come to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his leſſe profane followers. The <hi>Peripatetickes</hi> principall and moſt ſubtle argument, which alſo they vrge with greateſt vehemency, is briefly this; ſay they, either the world was from euerlaſting, or elſe made anew, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from not being, vnto this being which now it hath. But it was not made a new; for then, either it proceeded from a power and fitneſſe which it had to bee vnto this actuall being, or elſe it was made of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. If before it was actually ſubſiſting, it had a being potentiall from euerlaſting (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things that are potentially, though in the baſeſt degree of being, yet are not meerely nothing) it followeth, that it alwaies was (at leaſt potentially) and ſo eternall. If we ſay that it was made of nothing, that is (in their Philoſophy) an abſurd impoſſibility. For it is with them a principle not queſtionable, <hi>That euery making preſuppoſeth a ſubiect.</hi> Now if wee obiect, that the neceſſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a reall ſubiect dependeth only vpon
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22836:25"/>the Makers infirmity, and imperfection: they anſwer, <hi>that</hi> the diſability of doing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities is not defect or imbecillity. To which ſaid argument of theirs (as they would haue it) there may bee a double an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer giuen. For firſt, wee affirme that the world proceeded, from not being to being. To the propoſition of their proſyllogiſme we anſwer by deniall thereof, and reiect their diſtinction as ſophiſticall, putting contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (the greateſt oppoſition) betwixt things, not only agreeing, but euen all one. For there is a potentiall being, incident to things that are not at all, and therefore doe the Schoolemen diſtinguiſh of the potentiall being after this manner: A thing (ſay they) may bee ſaid to haue a potentiall being two waies: firſt, that is ſaid to bee potentially which is not yet, either in whole, or in part ſubſiſting in nature, which hauing no reall, or actuall cauſe of being, may notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding afterward haue a true cauſe of its eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and exiſtence. So that it is not any thing, in, or of it ſelfe, but is vertually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within the ability of ſome thing, that may afterward bring it vnto a true and reall being. As for example, there is a potentiall being of moe worlds then one, inaſmuch as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22836:25"/>God by his vnreſiſtable, vndecaied power is able, as well to make more worlds, as hee was to create this one world which wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and inhabite: yet, who will ſay, that there are more worlds then one, either to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally or partially, really and truely now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nature? Indeed it is a thing within the compaſſe of Gods omnipotencie, to bring in a multiplicitie of worlds, and therefore we may not vntruely ſay, that this multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of worlds hath a being potentiall. So likewiſe, who will denie, that a man ſound and without maime or lacke of his limmes, that neuer ſet foot ouer his threſhold, hath power (with ſuppoſition of health and ſtrength) to trauell ouer the whole circuit of the countrey; yet is it abſurd to ſay, that this iourney of his, is any way in nature, either wholly or in part. Secondly, that may iuſtly and is more properly ſaid; to be potential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that hauing an actuall and reall ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, euen ſeparate from it efficient cauſe, wherein it was before vertually contained, yet lacketh ſomewhat, which by nature it is capable of. As for inſtance hereof, a childe altogether vnlettred, may iuſtly be ſaid to be potentially diſpoſed toward the receit of learning, inaſmuch as it hath a reaſonable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22836:26"/>ſoule, which is alway accompanied with a capacitie of learning. To applie this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto our purpoſe, we ſay that to be potentially in the firſt degree, is indeed to be nothing; becauſe this potentiall being is a meere not being: &amp; ſo was the world from euerlaſting, hauing ſuch an abilitie and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pableneſſe (that I may ſo ſpeake) of being, foraſmuch as God by his omnipotency was from euerlaſting powerfull enough to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the world, as in time hee did actually make the ſame. Now for that other kinde of potentiall being, incident vnto things onely that haue receiued an actuall being from their cauſes, it was in that rude <hi>Chaos</hi> created by God, the firſt day of the begun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making of the world, and was afterward per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the worke of diſtinction (as the Schoole-men call it) when God out of that confuſion, or rather vpon that rude lumpe, brought this admirable varietie and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of creatures, for the ornament of the world: for that the world was in this ſort potentially onely at the creation of the firſt matter, which was in the time by <hi>Moſes</hi> mentioned. Secondly we anſwer, that it is not impoſſible for God of nothing to make things really and truly ſubſiſting, as we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22836:26"/>proued. To their <hi>Axiome</hi> or principle, which they call Vndeniable, we anſwer, that there is a twofolde faction or making: One naturall, incident to creatures, commonly called Generation; the other ſupernaturall, the priuiledge of God himſelfe, which we terme Creation. Now euery making which is a Generation, requireth a really-being ſubiect, becauſe it is either a motion or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which ſuppoſeth a matter wherein it is receiued: but the making of Creation, is alway without any matter ſubiect, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſined to be, <hi>A making ſomething of nothing:</hi> But theſe aduerſaries admit of no ſuch du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of making, holding it a meere impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie, for any Agent in this ſort to create: Thus therefore ſomewhat otherwiſe we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: There be two ſorts of Agents or Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, the one Vniuerſall, the other Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular or Partiall. They differ thus: That the Efficient vniuerſall is cauſe of the whole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eſſence of it effect, making both matter and forme: and this action of this Agent, is not Motion or Mutation, but a bare Emanation. The Particular Agent is not cauſe of the whole eſſence of that it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, ſeeing it alway requireth the preexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of the matter, and the action thereof
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22836:27"/>is truely called Motion or Mutation. So then, it is impoſſible for a partiall or halfe efficient (as you may terme him) to worke or make a thing of nothing; but for an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, it is not onely poſſible, but euen eaſie. And is it not (thinke you, to anſwer euery point of their reaſon) an infirmitie in the maker, not to bee able to make a thing without matter? for why is the exiſtence of the matter neceſſarie, but becauſe the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent can doe nothing: and doth not this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a defect of the workmans abilitie? No, ſay the aduerſaries, for it is no imperfection to be vnable to doe things impoſſible: but we denie that this is vnpoſſible vnto any, but vnto particular agents naturall; as for God to whom nothing is vnpoſſible (but to denie himſelfe) as he is the whole and ſole cauſe of being, ſo is he able, euen from a not being, to bring things to the higheſt and moſt excellent degree of being. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſay they, vnleſſe we grant an euer-being of motion, we muſt needs admit either of a proceeding <hi>in infinitum,</hi> or els of this ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>contradiction,</hi> that before the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there was a motion more ancient; two maine abſurdities, the one in reaſon, the other in nature. For the progreſſe <hi>in infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:22836:27"/>they thinke it is thus proued; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the motion, whereby the firſt mooued body was made, there was of neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite ſome potentiall being thing, becauſe that motion is only incident vnto things of a potentiall exiſtence. If that be granted, then they inferre, that there was ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherby this ſubiect had it being, and ſo <hi>in infinitum.</hi> But to ſtop their long iourney, wee may hinder this infinite proceeding by granting a creation. It is true indeed that there muſt needes bee a thing capable of motion before there can be any moouing: for in euery motion there is a thing moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and a thing mooued; but there is no neceſſitie that this mooueable ſhould haue its being by motion; for it was made by creation, which was no motion, but a ſimple and bare emanation: For there is a two-fold mediate action, whereby a cauſe is ſaid to worke, according to which duplicitie of action, they hane thus diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed of cauſes efficient. There is, ſay the Schoolemen, a double efficient or working cauſe, one called <hi>Efficiens per tranſmutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> that is, ſuch a cauſe, whoſe operation is alway ioined with ſome change in the thing working, according as is the reſiſtance, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22836:28"/>of the bodie betweene it, and the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, or of the thing whereon hee work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which doth more or leſſe withſtand his impreſſion. The other is, <hi>Efficiens per emanationem,</hi> as when without any repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of any patient or labour of the agent, the effect or worke doth voluntarily and freely ariſe from the action of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſe: as the ſhadow from the body: ſuch is God, whoſe vnreſiſtable power by his bare word of command, euen of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing made this admirable worke of the world, as the ſhadow and obſcure repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his wiſedome and omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: not changed in his nature, there being nothing by <hi>Reaction</hi> to imprint any thing in the impaſſionable <hi>Godhead.</hi> And this is the full and ſufficient anſwer to the ſecond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. Thirdly they reaſon thus: There is an eternall mouer, therefore there hath bene an eternall motion and a thing moued, in aſmuch as theſe relatiues cannot be but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in nature. For anſwer whereto wee muſt remember, that there is an abſolute, both conſideration, and being of God. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute I ſay and out of relation, otherwiſe Gods being ſhould be onely in relation. It is true indeed that relatiues are alway toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22836:28"/>in nature beginning to be, and finiſhing their being, in one and the ſame moment. For inſtance, a father is not a father vntill he haue a ſonne, nor is he a father longer than he hath a ſonne. And yet for all that thoſe things which are Relatiues, may haue being, one before another, thogh not as Relatiues, yet as things really ſubſiſting in nature. For example, who can deny that <hi>Adam</hi> was in nature, before either conception or birth of his bloody ſonne <hi>Cain?</hi> yet was he not a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vntill God had bleſſed him with that after-curſed-ofspring. And who ſeeth not, that the Carpenter had being in Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he builds the houſe, although he be no actuall builder till the houſe be in making? So God that was from euerlaſting before all times, had his being without motion, though not as a mouer, yet as a thing really and perfectly exiſting: but when in fulneſſe of time (according to the free determined purpoſe of his will) he began the frame of the world, then alſo began he to be a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, a builder in reſpect of this goodly houſe and palace, the world; <hi>a Father,</hi> that is, the Beginning of being vnto the childe of the creation, the image of his <hi>greatneſſe;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in theſe and ſuch kinde of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22836:29"/>we muſt warily vſe theſe termes of rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſpecially in regard of the creatures, leſt wee binde God onely vnto a relatiue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo make his exiſtence dependent on the creatures.</p>
            <p>Their fourth argument is in ſubſtance this: If God ſo long before had being, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being a Creator, there was doubtleſſe ſome defect in the foregoing time, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie whereof in the moment of creation mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to make the world rather at that time than any other. For there is no new action but preſuppoſeth ſome new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citement, which moued the Agent to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the worke, more then before; but there could bee nothing at this time more than before, that could moue God the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and perfecteſt workeman, to take in hand this buſieneſſe and worke rather now, than before; for then how could he be the primary and principall cauſe? But this in ſhort may be the anſwer; Indeed there was all this time an impediment, foraſmuch as God would not actually create, vntill the time foreappointed in his ſecret purpoſe was accompliſhed. Nay, but ſay the aduerſaries, God vntill this time was indifferent to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, or not to create, therefore there was in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22836:29"/>the inſtant of the creation ſome thing that reſtrained this his indifferency. But we may anſwer, That there was no ſuch indifferency, (as they talke of,) God hauing from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, purpoſely determined at this time to beginne the worke of the creation. So that vnto the fore-mentioned demand of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, why God deferred the creating of the world vntill this moment of time, we may anſwer, that of the choiſe of this time, rather then any other, for this his worke, there can no other reaſon be giuen, but his moſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, that in his decree of creation reſtrained, and bound it ſelfe to this time, rather than vnto any other. Now if they ſhall reply, that we are not to imagine Gods will vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and therefore no doubt there was ſome reaſon that mooued him to this limitation of his will: we may anſwer, That we doe not deny but God had ſome reaſon (though not without himſelfe) of this his prorogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Nay we may without offence, goe ſo farre, as to giue ſome reaſon of this dilation, in generall: That God would not from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting create the world, to ſhew the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency of his exiſtence in regard of the creatures: as alſo, to giue vs vnderſtand, that not for any hope of benefit, which ſhould
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22836:30"/>proceed to him from the creatures, he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke this worke: but rather (as it is the property of goodneſſe to communicate it ſelfe) out of the ouerflowing fountaine of his indefectiue <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> to deriue ſome commodity vnto vs his creatures: for hee that could ſo long be without vs, might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any inconueniency vnto himſelfe, for euer haue continued in that ſtate of <hi>loneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> So that, of the deferring of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in generall, there may be a reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; but why hee began at this time rather than at any other, either before or after, there is no other reaſon, but his owne free-will, knowen vnto vs. But heere ariſeth a doubt, whether God could haue begun ſooner, or put off longer this worke of creation. The anſwer is, that he could by his potential and abſolute power; he could not by his actuall and conditionall. For Gods power hath a two-fold conſideration, the one abſolute, without regard of any his decrees whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, whereby he is able to do all, euen thoſe things, that he will not; the other conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ioined with the conſideration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his will, whereby he is able to doe all things which hee will, and onely thoſe things which he will. God therefore, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22836:30"/>without his decree, was able, ſooner or later to create the world; but if we conſider him together with his purpoſe, hee could not either haue preuented, or deferred this his intended worke of the creation: Nor do we heereby robbe God of his freedome, or binde him to any part of the contradiction, but if hee bee bound, ſure hee hath bound himſelfe, hauing this law onely preſcibed him, that he denie not himſelfe, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to take away his Godhead. But if God would not from euerlaſting make the world, how is he not changed in his will? The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, that God would from euerlaſting make the world, but he would not make the world from euerlaſting; that is in plainer tearmes: God had from euerlaſting a will and purpoſe to create the world, but it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was his will, that the world ſhould haue a coeternall being with himſelfe; ſo that Gods will is ſtil the ſame altogether vnalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But they farther vrge this argument, demanding how God by an euerlaſting and old action of his wil, could in time create the world anew, remaining himſelfe vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. To which we may anſwer, that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued action of his will, how ancient ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, executing onely that which he before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22836:31"/>intended, may well ſtand without admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of alteration: as for example, If the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of my will to day, be to iourney toward London the next weeke, which alſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto purpoſe I performe; will any man ſay my will is changed? In like ſort, <hi>God</hi> from euerlaſting decreeing to create the world at ſuch a time, if at the time purpoſed this his decree be put in execution, is not thereby changed. Nay rather he is thereby to be thought more vnchangeable, for as much as he performeth that which before he did determine. Why but, ſay they, God is not freed from alteration, becauſe that of a <hi>Non-creator,</hi> hee was made a <hi>Creator.</hi> The anſwer is, That God was not heereby changed, albeit there was indeed ſome change (though improperly ſo called) when as the world proceeded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not being vnto being: for the ſucceſſion of a being, after a not being, importeth ſome alteration, thogh not in the author of the new being, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the thing that receiued that being; we ſhall make it plaine by this ſuppoſition. Let vs imagine a vault or other cloſe place, ſo fenced from the Sunne beames that no light, not the leaſt glimmering can pierceit, which afterward by digging or ſome ſuch
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22836:31"/>meanes, may haue paſſage made thorough it, for the Sunnes acceſſe; would we ſay that the Sunne were by this meanes altered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it inlightneth a place which before was full of darkneſſe? Euen ſo, and much more ſo, God the fountaine of Light, (whoſe <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit moouing vpon the waters,</hi> whereas before <hi>there was darkneſſe vpon the face of the deepe,</hi> enlightned that darkneſſe, diſtinguiſhing thoſe things which before were confuſedly mixed, or rather bringing them from <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> to this their perfection) is not at all altered, but ſtill remaineth the ſame, euer vnchangeable. And indeed, if euery new worke of God ſhould make him changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how ſhould hee not be often changed, creating daily the ſoules of now liuing men? For to ſay they haue being before their ioin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto the body, is plainly hereticall, and <hi>Origen</hi> was in that behalfe accuſed of a verie groſſe error. Nor is it likely, nor yet indeed poſſible, they ſhould come by <hi>traduction</hi> or propagation from our parents. For our ſoules being as the Angels are <hi>Spirituall ſubſtances,</hi> are as farre from that abilitie of procreation, as the Angels are, thoſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall celeſtiall creatures: and there is the like reaſon for both. The Angels by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22836:32"/>reaſon of their ſpiritualitie, are void and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of procreation, mens ſoules alſo being no leſſe ſpirituall than the Angels, are alſo vnfit for procreation: therefore one ſoule begets not another, much leſſe comes it of a corporall ſeed, it ſelfe being ſpirituall. It remaines therefore that they are then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new created by God, and ſo coupled vnto their bodies. Neither is God for this cauſe changed, ſeeing, as is aforeſaid, he doth now onely put in execution, that which before he had in intention; and therefore (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this whole argument, with that ſaying of <hi>Hugo de Sancto Victore</hi>) <hi>Gods will was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and the worke of his will was temporary; for alwaies euen from Eternitie, he had a will to create the world; yet neuer was he purpoſed to make the world from euerlaſting, but his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and will was to make that in time which hee purpoſed before time to make in time. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by his euer being goodneſſe he for euer pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed: by his eternall wiſedome hee alway diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that, which by his euerlaſting power he once compoſed.</hi> Fiftly, they reaſon from the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of time, in this ſort. Time is Eternall, therefore there is alſo an Eternall motion; for Time is the meaſure of moouing. Now the antecedent is thus prooued: That which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22836:32"/>hath beene alway, and ſhall be for euer, is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall; but ſuch is the condition of time: for you can deſigne vs no moment or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant before which, Time was not, and after which, Time ſhall not remaine. For, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, euery <hi>now,</hi> or inſtant of time is the end of time paſt, and begining of time to come: as in a right line, euery middle point is the end of the fore-part of the line, and the beginning of the part fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. To which we may anſwer by reiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this their diſcription of time, for, (as <hi>Scaliger</hi> hath well obſerued) motion is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the meaſure of time; and thence it is (as I take it) that <hi>Plato</hi> called the Sunne and Starres times Inſtruments, and as it were the <hi>Iacobs ſtaffe</hi> of time; becauſe by their motion and dircumuolution we meaſure the indurance of the world. And therefore alſo (as I conceiue of it) the <hi>Poets</hi> called Saturne, that is Time, Heauens Sonne, becauſe that from their circular mouing, came the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Daies, and Moneths, and Yeeres. And to ſay the truth, there is a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and true definition of times then this of <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> and it is this: <hi>The paſt, preſent and future indurance of things:</hi> Which alſo the authours of this diſcription diſtinguiſh into
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22836:33"/>it kinds. There is (ſay they) a time perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, or eternall, Gods owne peculiar attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, who alone indureth from generation to generation; and there is an indurance or Time momentary, incident vnto the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. In this ſenſe therefore it is no abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to ſay, there was a time when <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> time was not: for hee maketh time of the ſame age with the heauens motion, ſo that, vntill the heauens began to bee mooued, <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> time was not: yet was there time before the heauens creation, that is a long ſpace of indurance, in which God alone had being: But becauſe time is indeed proper vnto the creatures, being as (other bodily and ſpirituall creatures) in ſcripture ſaid to be made by God, let vs follow <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his owne Definition, and to his obiection out of his <hi>Schoole-interpreters</hi> we may fetch this anſwer: That euery <hi>Now,</hi> and inſtant of time is not both beginning of time to come and end of time paſt: for there is a threefold inſtant or <hi>Now.</hi> The firſt is <hi>inſtans,</hi> or <hi>Nunc initiatiuum,</hi> an inſtant onely of beginning. The ſecond they tearme, <hi>Nunc continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum,</hi> a continuing inſtant, and that is both beginning in reſpect of time following, and end in regard of time paſt. There is a third
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22836:33"/>inſtant or moment, and that they call <hi>Nunc finiens,</hi> or <hi>terminatiuum,</hi> and that is ſuch an inſtant, as only is an end of time foregoing: They may all bee thus illuſtrated, as in a ſtraight line, the firſt pricke or point is onely the begining of the line, the laſt point onely the end of the ſame, the reſt in the middle are both, the end of that part of the line which was before drawn, and the beginning of the hinder part. So in time, we may point out an <hi>inſtant</hi> that is onely <hi>beginning,</hi> another that is onely an <hi>end,</hi> a third that is both a <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> and <hi>end. Ariſtotle</hi> his authority there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can truely be vnderſtood onely of the continuing and coupling inſtant. But againſt this diſtinguiſhing anſwer, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath this exception: If there be any ſuch <hi>inſtant,</hi> as is only a <hi>beginning</hi> in reſpect of time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llowing, and no <hi>end</hi> of that time which went before, then before this <hi>inſtant</hi> there was no time. What then? Therefore there was an <hi>Ante</hi> without time, which is abſurd. For <hi>Ante</hi> and <hi>Poſt, before</hi> and <hi>after,</hi> are differences of time: As for example: When we ſay, <hi>Philip</hi> liued before <hi>Alexander,</hi> this word <hi>before,</hi> ſignifies a difference in time, betwixt <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> his ſonnes being. But who ſeeth not more ſubtilty than ſoundneſſe in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22836:34"/>of <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> for we will in like ſort thus reaſon againſt him. In his Phyſicks he hath this <hi>Poſition, Extra coelum nullus eſt locus:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond heauen there is no place; therefore, there is ſome <hi>extra,</hi> in which is no place. For <hi>extra</hi> and <hi>intra, without</hi> and <hi>within,</hi> are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of place; as for example: when we ſay he is without doores, our meaning is, that he is in ſome place without the houſe. Now if wee ſhould thus reaſon againſt <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> There is out of <hi>heauen</hi> a roome or place to be in; for <hi>extra</hi> without, is a difference of place, things being ſaid to be without onely in regard of place. But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith <hi>extra coelum,</hi> therefore there is without the inward hollow compaſſe of heauen an external out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roome: would he not ſtraight (and that iuſtly) reproue our ſophiſtrie? for <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his meaning in that place is, that all things whatſoeuer are conteined within the inſide of the body of <hi>heauen:</hi> and it is as if hee had ſaid, there is no place, but within the inſide of the ouercaſt circle of <hi>heauen.</hi> In like ſort, when we ſay that before this firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the heauens motion, there was no time; our meaning is, that all reall time had beginning with the heauens mouing. <hi>Reall time,</hi> I ſay; for there is <hi>time</hi> only imaginarie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22836:34"/>improperly called <hi>time,</hi> as being rather a part of eternitie, and of that indurance and long continuance, which wee conceiue to haue beene in God before the creation of the world. And thus ſhall wee reade the words, <hi>Before,</hi> and <hi>After,</hi> vſed among the ancient Writers both Chriſtian and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane: for ſo did <hi>Ouid</hi> vſe it in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his <hi>Metamorphoſis; Ante mare &amp; terras, &amp; quod tegit omnia coelum:</hi> Before that heauen and earth was made. So in the Scripture: <hi>Before the foundations of the world were layd, thou art God from euerlaſting, world without end.</hi> Where it ſignifies no true and really ſubſiſting time, for this time began only with the motions of the <hi>heauens,</hi> as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> himſelfe witneſſeth. In briefe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to ſhut vp this argument and this whole controuerſie: The firſt inſtant and moment of time reall (before mentioned) was both a <hi>beginning</hi> and <hi>end; a beginning</hi> of <hi>time reall,</hi> and an <hi>end</hi> of <hi>time imaginary:</hi> nor is it any abſurdity to ſay, that <hi>time imaginary</hi> was before <hi>true and really ſubſiſting time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> And thus haue we with all poſſible ſpeed runne ouer the reaſons which be vſually brought to proue the worlds being from euerlaſting; let vs now with like or leſſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22836:35"/>breuitie paſſe ouer thoſe reaſons which ſerue to improue this errour: and they are only two, which we will but propound, auoiding ouer-tedious long diſcourſe; and ſo go on to the other part of the queſtion. Firſt then, from our owne experience we reaſon thus: It is a trueth confirmed by the triall of all times, that the quantities of mens bodies haue a perceiuable impairing, as alſo the length and continuance of their liues: ſo that, if in that infinit ſpace of foregoing time men had had being (as without queſtion, the world was neuer void of men, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and moſt noble member thereof) through continuall and inceſſant decay, their bodies had beene brought to as little a quantitie as they are capable of, if not cleane conſumed: but we ſee their quantitie is not yet come vnto the loweſt; therefore had they not being from euerlaſting. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly and more ſpecially, had this world beene from euerlaſting, infinite alſo had beene the propagation of man; and ſo wee ſhould bring into the world an actuall infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſſe, as abſurd in Nature as Parolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes be in Logicke: for in this infinite ſpace and generation there had beene an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of mens ſoules, which being
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22836:35"/>by Nature vncapable of mortalitie, we can not ſay, that as one was created another was deſtroied, and ſo ſhould there be an <hi>infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in regard of number, actually ſubſiſting in Nature. And thus hoping that ſmall power will ſerue to confound an aduerſary already ouercome, wee paſſe to the other part of the Queſtion, purpoſing as much breuitie as its difficultie and obſcuritie will beare.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion is touching the worlds im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, whether, as it had a beginning of being, ſo it ſhall alſo haue an end. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> when hee firſt heard of their opinion, who appointed an end vnto the world, ſcoffingly burſt out into theſe words: <hi>I was once afraid that my houſe, either by force of tempeſt, or by iniury of time, or laſtly by ſome defect in the workeman-ſhip, ſhould haue ſuddenly ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med me, but now I haue great cauſe to feare my owne and my houſes ruine, becauſe of thoſe that in words goe about to pull downe the world.</hi> But for the plainer and more ſpeedy proceeding in the controuerſie, let vs in one word ſet downe the true meaning of the queſtion. There is a twofold end, the one of <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the other of <hi>annihilation:</hi> the end of <hi>corruption,</hi> I call that whereby a thing is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22836:36"/>changed from <hi>being</hi> to a not <hi>being,</hi> not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie as if it ceaſed altogether to be in nature, but becauſe it loſeth that <hi>being</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had; as for example, when wood by force of fire is turned into aſhes, we may not vntruely ſay, there is a corruption of the wood, foraſmuch as it ceaſeth to be wood, &amp; is become aſhes; yet can we not ſay, heere is any annihilation, for we ſee there is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance remaining, but the matter which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was vnder the forme of wood, hath now put on the form of aſhes, &amp; ſo of wood cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted are aſhes generated, according to that worne axiome of <hi>Ariſtotle, That the corruption of one thing is the generation of an other.</hi> The end of annihilation is, when a thing ſo loſeth its preſent being, that no part thereof, neither matter nor yet forme abideth any longer in nature; but as it firſt was made of nothing, ſo is it againe turned into nothing. The queſtion then (as I take it) muſt be thus vnderſtood, that the world ſhall haue an end, though not of annihilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet of corruption; that is in other terms, though it ſhall not vtterly be aboliſhed and turned vnto nothing, (for the matter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall ſtill remaine) yet ſhall it be changed into another eſtate and condition. The firſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22836:36"/>part of the aſſertion is prooued by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the learned. For <hi>Plato</hi> witneſſeth in his <hi>Timaeus;</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Bochus</hi> and <hi>Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> and <hi>Damaſcene</hi> in his ſecond booke <hi>viz. of Orthodoxal faith:</hi> teſtified alſo by the wiſe <hi>Salomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 3. <hi>I haue learned</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>that all the works of the Lord indure for euer.</hi> that is, as I interpret it, though not without corruption, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out annihilation. Now whether they haue this ſtate of corruption by nature or no, there is a great queſtion: but we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably anſwer, that of themſelues and their naturall diſpoſition infuſed by God, they haue no naturall inclination, or deſire of corruption, much leſſe of annihilation, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as euery thing hath a naturall loue of its being, and an innated hatred of all things that bee enemies vnto the ſame, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by that naturall Sympathie and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathie which may be obſerued in things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of reaſon: for ſo we ſee in experience the <hi>lambe</hi> which neuer had experience of the woolues crueltie, euen at the firſt ſight doth tremble and flie for feare. Nay, in creatures of a lower degree then theſe, tearmed by <hi>Ariſtotle, Plant-animals,</hi> wee may obſerue, the like antipathie. <hi>Scaliger</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:22836:37"/>reporteth of a tree, growing in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince which hee calles <hi>Pudefatamea,</hi> that at a mans neere approching, for modeſty, draweth in his farre-ſpreadding boughes, at his departure ſpreeds it ſelfe againe, for that cauſe tearmed by the inhabitants, the <hi>ſhame-faſt-tree.</hi> But wee may more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably attribute this it contraction, to a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall diuining (as it were) and fore-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that it hath of ſome harme, whereof it is in danger, as may be proportionably gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the like behauiour in other things of the ſame kinde. For ſo <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> writeth of the <hi>Spongies</hi> that (when a man puts foorth his hand to diſplace them, as alſo before a tempeſt) ſhrinke vp together on a heape, a if they meant to ſhift for themſelues, either by flight, or elſe by vniting their diſperſed forces, for the ſtronger reſiſtance: which are euident proofes of that naturall ingrafted deſire in all things to preſerue there being. For whereas the firſt matter is ſaid to deſire corruption, for that as not contented with the forme it preſently enioieth, it deſireth an other, whereupon followes the expulſion of the former before inherent: the anſwer it, that in this laboring to procure an other forme, then that it had: it intends not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22836:37"/>but rather perfection, not diſliking the form incumbent, ſeeing it deſireth both; but as <hi>Eſopsdogge,</hi> ſnatching greedily at the ſhadow which he thought had beene a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, meant not to loſe that which he had faſt hold of in his teeth. So the firſt matter greedily caried to the deſire of many formes wherein indeede conſiſteth its perfection, loſeth that which before it had: for as much as by a law of Nature, <hi>Two formes of diuers, not ſubordinate, kinds, are at the ſame time vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable together.</hi> So then it deſires perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in ſteed therof accidentally gaineth corruption &amp; expulſion of the preexiſtent <hi>forme.</hi> Nothing therefore ſimply deſires it owne corruption, but ſo as it may tend to it further perfection, &amp; conſummation, much leſſe its vtter abolition. For as much as it is farre better to be in the vileſt and moſt baſe degree of being, then not to be at all. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the annihilation of the world ſhal not be of it ſelfe, nor yet by any meanes internall. Nor can it proceed from any external natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall agent, no not that vniuerſal fore menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned nature is able to bring it vnto nothing: For as nature cannot make ſome thing of nothing, ſo neither is ſhe of power ſufficient to bring a thing from being, to an vtter not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22836:38"/>being at all, hauing a limited and finit pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. To which purpoſe a learned frier ſaid excellently well. That, <hi>the firſt maker of all things in reſpect of its being and not being, is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect onely vnto Gods wil, permitted to the rule of Naturall agents onely in regard of tranſmutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For a Naturall agent may induce or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell a forme either ſubſtantial or accidentall. But how farre ſoeuer mans Power or Nature is caried in fury, laboring by might and maine towards an vtter ruinating, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of things, yet ſhall it neuer attaine vnto <hi>Annihilation.</hi> They may indeed by tyrannous inflicting of death, make that which is neere the matter of a man, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a carcaſe, they may alſo with fire, burne the dead corps, but though a thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand woods ſhould bee ſpent in burning of one poore carcaſe, yet were they neuer able vtterly to annihilate and bring it vnto no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. So that Nature is too weake to cauſe Annihilation. But yet ſaie the ſcrupulous aduerſaries, God who by his infinite and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall power was able of nothing to make the world, is by the ſame his boundles power able at his pleaſure to returne it to nothing. It is true indeed &amp; out of queſtion, that God by his abſolute vndecaied pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22836:38"/>is ſufficient as well to diſtroy the world as he was at the beginning, to make it: by his abſolute power (I ſay) conſidered without regard of his will, but if we reſpect his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, reſtrained by his will: that is regard what he will and hath decreed to do if by his word we may learne his will, we may truly anſwer, that God himſelfe cannot annihilate the word, becauſe he can do nothing that impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth contradiction, or that any way importeth mutability, whereby of God he ſhould be made no God. Nor do we heerby take away his omnipotency, nay rather we eſtabliſh his power, it being a chiefe point of infirmity and weakeneſſe, to bee capable of change, and able to deny it ſelfe: but God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed not to annihilate the world, therefore he cannot now turne it vnto nothing, how then (may ſome man ſay) ſhall it haue an end, for if neither of it ſelfe it incline, nor can be by any meanes naturall inforced to Annihilation, no nor God himſelf can turne it into nothing, what end ſhall it haue? The anſwer is, that as man hath his end by death, whereas, notwithſtand his ſoule is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, his body is onely changed into its firſt matter, not turned into nothing: ſo the world though incapeable of annihilation, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22836:39"/>hath beene proued, yet hath in it an end vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitable, when it ſhall be changed from the preſent corrupt eſtate into a far more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and heauenly condition of indurance and immortality. But heere ariſeth a doubt, moued by thoſe ſcoffers that <hi>Peter</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied ſhould come in the laſt daies, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, <hi>Where is the promiſe of his comming: For ſince the father fell on ſleepe, all things haue continued alike from the beginning of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Where by the way, let vs obſerue that they make the time of Chriſts comming, and the end of the world, things of one and the ſame ſignification, ſo that as many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſcripture, as warrant the certainty of Chriſts comming, ſerue alſo to proue the worlds end and diſſolution. To their reaſon we may anſwer with <hi>Peter,</hi> that the worlds long and hither to vnchanged continuance, is no ſure proofe of impoſſibility to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied. For God that by his bare word could of nothing make the world, can now alſo with as great facrlity alter the ſtate of the ſame. But their ſuppoſition is moſt vntrue, for the world hath not from the beginning continued in the ſame ſtate vnaltred, the whole earth being in <hi>Noahs</hi> floud ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with waters. But to this they may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:22836:39"/>that it was no generall or vniuerſall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, being extended onely to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing creatures, &amp; they alſo in part preſerued in <hi>Noahs</hi> arke. It is true indeed, that this was onely a particular or partial deſtruction, the heauens remaining altogether vntouched, the other elements alſo incorrupted. But yet this ſheweth a change in the worlds eſtate which they ſeemed to deny. Touching the generall diſtinction of all things, <hi>Peter</hi> after anſwereth; to which place we wil refer them: But that wherein the difficulty of the whole controuerſie conſiſteth is the immutable eſtate of the heauenly bodies wherein hath beene obſerued by experience of all ages, a conſtancy almoſt admirable: when in this ſublunary region of elementiſh bodies, there hath beene as great variety, and almoſt a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular alteration. And indeed, were the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens capable of corruption, how could the ſpheare of the Moone, ſituated ſo neere the fire haue continued ſo long vnconſumed. Let vs therfore a little examine how the cauſe ſtands: with the heauens in the matter of corruption.</p>
            <p>There are two different opinions of them that make the heauens incorruptible, ſome to deliuer them from corruption, haue made
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:22836:40"/>them void of all matter, others allot them a matter, but in a diſtinct kinde from that of the ſublunary bodies, all agreeing, that they be incorruptible. The chiefe of the firſt ſect, is <hi>Auerroes,</hi> a learned Turke, who expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the matter with vs, demands by what meanes we came to know the matter of the heauens? For the onely meanes to prooue the exiſtence of matter in any thing, is, as he calleth it, <hi>Subſtantiall tranſmutation;</hi> or more plainely, the <hi>ſucceſſion of formes.</hi> But in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen there hath beene no ſuch ſucceſſion, no nor any alteration of qualities, therefore the heauens are <hi>immateriall.</hi> But wee may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, firſt that the being of matter in anie thing is knowen as wel by accidentary, or lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, as by <hi>ſubſtantiall tranſmutation.</hi> But the heauens haue a locall Motion, or Mutation, at leaſt in their parts, therfore they conſiſt of matter. Secondly we anſwer thus, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the heauens haue all this while laſted without change in their ſubſtance, yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are capable of future tranſmutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we may thence conclude the preſence of matter in them. For who would ſay that there is in a ſucking child no reaſonable ſoul becauſe he ſeeth in him no actuall vſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or preſent conceit of learning, we know
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22836:40"/>that his potentiall diſpoſition and ſitneſſe to conceiue, is teſtimony ſufficient of that ſoule which is in him. Their ſecond argument is this, all things conſiſting of a corporall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are withall corruptible for the ability of receiuing the yet abſent formes being a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie inſeparable from the matter, which alſo is accompanied with a longing deſire to ſupply its defects, there muſt needs be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an expulſion of the incumbent forme for induction of a new ſucceſſor, wherein is corruption; or els this, The matters incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ingrafted deſire, as it were, muſt be alway fruſtrate, which folly, the moſt wiſe God of Nature deteſteth: therfore there is in the heauens no ſuch matter as we talke of. To which argument, they that make the matter of the celeſtiall bodies different from that of the ſublunary creatures, frame this anſwer: Indeed (ſay they) whatſoeuer is compounded of ſuch a matter as this is, of the ſublunary creatures, is ſubiect vnto cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; but the heauens haue a matter of a different and farre more excellent ſtate than theſe vnder elements, and that is the ſum and foundation of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his opinion and reaſon touching the heauens incorruptible condition. But we that make one matter of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:22836:41"/>both, may thus ſomewhat probably anſwer: That though ſuch a matter is alway accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a capableneſſe of corruption, yet may it by ſome ſuperior ouerruling pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be preſerued from all actuall cotruption. And ſo ſtandeth the caſe with the heauens, which neuer had beene able of themſelues ſo long to haue continued without alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but by the helpe of ſome higher power; not as the Peripateticks and Platonicks fondly imagine the Angels or Intelligences (which <hi>Alcinous</hi> calleth Leſſer gods) but by the ſoueraigne appointment of God, who to moderate and ſtay the too frequent and ouerhaſtie alteration of the vnder bodies, hath allotted the heauens this regularity and vniformitie of motion. But heere they will demand a reaſon, what hath ſo fulfilled the matters deſire of interchangeable ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of formes, that it remaineth contented with that forme which it preſently inioyeth. The anſwer is: That either the excellencie of the forme preſent cauſeth this content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or els Gods appointment ouerſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth its deſire. How then? Are we Patrons or rather Authours of violence in thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent agreeing bodies? Nay rather, by the limitation of the matters vnſtayed indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22836:41"/>we doe more eſtabliſh that their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent harmonie. For as in a city ſituate on the confines of two diſagreeing kingdomes, of it ſelfe inclining to neither ſide, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different for entertainment of either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering aduerſarie, if after valourous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt performed by one partie, it yeeldeth it ſelfe to the vanquiſhers dominion, and by the prouident induſtrious care of the new ſuperuiſor, be fortified againſt the violent irruption of the forevanquiſhed aduerſaries; by this new reſtraint of its old indifferencie ſuffereth no violence, but rather is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in a quiet and peaceable condition within it ſelfe: ſo the matter of the celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bodies, howſoeuer naturally indifferent to entertaine any forme, if by the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring action of ſome preuailing Agent it be poſſeſſed of ſo excellent and powerfull a forme, as admits of no outward new impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in this limitation of its equall inſtable for diſpoſition, is not any way violenced, but rather fitter for the intended harmonie of the celeſtiall bodies. And that may ſerue for a ſufficient reaſon of the hitherto-incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted condition of the celeſtiall bodies. Now touching their future eſtate, we ſhall after diſpute, if firſt wee haue their fourth argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:22836:42"/>for diſproofe of the matter, as alſo the ſubſtance of their opinion. <hi>Auerroes</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith, that heauen is a forme of a ſelfe-ſubſiſtence; immaterial, dimenſional, local<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mooueable, participating light and other accidents; wherein (me thinketh) is a plaine contradiction: for to omit the diſquiſition, whether any forme can conſiſt without mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, what is more abſurd then to imagine quantitie really ſeparate from the matter, quantitie hauing its baſis and foundation in the matter, and onely limitation from the forme? farther, whatſoeuer is capable of real diuiſion, hath this capabilitie (that I may ſo terme it) from the matter: <hi>Reall diuiſion,</hi> I ſay, for the Mathematicians proportionably to their mentall abſtraction or ſeparation of quantitie, haue alſo a mentall diuiſion, but whatſoeuer hath quantity, is capable of ſuch a diuiſion, therefore alſo it hath a matter. Ouer and beſide all this, whatſoeuer is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueable by ſenſe, hath a matter; for the forme of nothing can be perceiued by ſenſe, but is vnderſtood and conceiued by its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the matter: but the heauen is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, therefore alſo materiall. To this adde <hi>Auerroes</hi> his owne teſtimonie, ſet downe in his Comment vpon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his ſeuenth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22836:42"/>booke of Metaphyſicks, wherein himſelfe confeſſeth, that accidents are inſeparable companions of the firſt Matter; but the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen (by his owne authoritie in the firſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged place) hath in it light and other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents inherent, how then is it altogether voide of matter? Other arguments taken from the inherencie of qualities peculiarly incident vnto things materiall, for breuities ſake I omit, haſtning to the ſecond Patrons of the heauens immortalitie, that doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a compoſition of a matter and a forme in the celeſtiall bodies, but will haue it a different and a diſtinct kinde from the elementiſh matter of the vnder bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Touching the ſenſe of the queſtion, <hi>Plato</hi> and ſome of his followers in this error, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it, as if when we ſay, the heauens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of elementary matter, wee meant that they are ſo compounded of the elements, as are mixt bodies heere below: whereupon ſome of the more ancient ſectaries in this kinde, as <hi>Heraclitus</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras</hi> thought that it was made of <hi>fire: Thales</hi> and <hi>Anaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes,</hi> of <hi>earth; Empedocles,</hi> of a medley of <hi>aire</hi> and <hi>fire; Plato</hi> himſelfe, of the <hi>foure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements,</hi> or (as <hi>Proclus</hi> recordeth his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) of the <hi>quinteſſence</hi> of them: whoſe refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:22836:43"/>we omit, as impertinent vnto our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: for our meaning is not that the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are the matter whereof the heauens be made, but thus we vnderſtand it, that the matter of the Ethereall and Elementiſh bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies is of the ſame <hi>kinde;</hi> the whole firſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being diuided into theſe principal parts, as into halfes, the one halfe vnited vnto the formes celeſtiall, the other halfe coupled vnto the formes of the elements: and ſo (as I conceiue) is that place in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to be vnderſtood, where it is ſaid, that <hi>In the beginning God created the Heauen and the Earth,</hi> that is, the matter whereof <hi>heauen</hi> and the <hi>elements</hi> were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards made, ſignified vnto vs by the name of thoſe <hi>waters wherupon the ſpirit of God was mooued:</hi> and mee thinketh the argument is very ſound, which is commonly alleged by our partakers: for as in other kindes of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, there is one, firſt &amp; principall whereunto all the reſt are reduced, ſo alſo in this kinde of the Matter, there being the like reaſon of al. But if we diſtinguiſh the Matter of the heauens fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of the elements, we can not come to one firſt Matter of al things; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is the ſame Matter both of the celeſtial &amp; inferior bodies, to which we may
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:22836:43"/>adde that thredbare argument of the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, <hi>Wit hout neceſſity we muſt not imagine a pluralitie in Nature,</hi> foraſmuch as Nature abhorreth vanitie: but there is no neceſſitie of the matters pluralitie; for the maine ground of this diſtinction (for ought that I can ſee) is, leſt they ſhould bee forced to grant a power in the heauens tending to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which (as is before ſaid) hath no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary illation, foraſmuch as the excellency of the forme preſent, reſtraineth the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring indifferent deſire of the matter, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the violent impreſſion of forren quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that ſhould breed rebellion of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect creatures, againſt their commander the heauens. But touching their reaſons, (in my poore opinion) they are very inſufficient: for firſt thus they diſpute: The formes of the ſublunary bodies may be ſeparated from their matter, but the heauens forme is vnſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable: when in my iudgement they proue rather a diſtinction of formes, than any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerfity of the matter. Or if they thence prooue a diuerſity of matter, becauſe the formes incident, are of greater and leſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, one in reſpect of an other, we may as well ſay, that the body of a man is of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct matter from that of the other more
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:22836:44"/>baſe creatures, becauſe his form is ſo paſſing excellent. Or if they reſtraine their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon onely to the power of ſeparation, that becauſe the matter of the heauens is ioyned inſeparably to the forme, when contrariwiſe the elementiſh matter hath often ſeparation, therefore there is not the ſame matter of both: wee anſwer, that the ſame matter in <hi>kinde,</hi> may ſo inſeparably bee vnited to its forme, as that it can neuer be ſeioyned: not that we deny a power of future ſeparation of the heauens matter from the preſent forme, but that this may bee a ſufficient reaſon of their hitherto inſeparable vnion. A ſecond argument is that of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſaith he, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer things participate the ſame matter, are capable of mutable tranſmutation, but the heauens can neuer bee changed into the inferior bodies, for ſomuch as the elements are altogether paſſiuely diſpoſed for receit of the heauens action, without any reacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon the heauens, therefore there is not the ſame matter of both. To which we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the propoſition or firſt ſentence muſt be vnderſtood of a potentiall tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and that with this exception; vnleſſe the matters imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be perfected by the formes inherent excellency, or reſiſtance be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:22836:44"/>made of ſome ſuperiour forme, to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the violence of the oppugning agent. We ſay that the forme now being in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, is of ſo powerfull and vnconquerable a nature, as that no naturall contrary agent is able to compaſie any the leaſt new impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thirdly thus they reaſon: Were the heauens of the ſame matter with the bodies of the elements, then in like fort ſhould they (at leaſt by nature) be corruptible; but the corruption is altogether abhorrent from the heauens nature. To which aſſumption <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen</hi> anſwers by a flat deniall, for euen the heauens in his Philoſophie are naturally ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption. To which accordeth that of <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Timaeus,</hi> that attributes the heauens incorruptiblenes to a ſuperior more powerfull cauſe. For ſo hee brings in the maker of the world ſpeaking vnto the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall bodies; <hi>By nature you are diſſoluble, but through my will preſerued from diſſolution. Nor ſhall the deſtintes of death preuaile ouer you, to deſtroy you, becauſe my will is a bond of more power to keepe you from corruption, than that wherewith at your firſt making you were holden together.</hi> And thus haue we haſtily runne ouer the difficult queſtion of the heauens matter. Touching the certainty and meanes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:22836:45"/>of their diſſolution we will briefly ſpeake by and by, after the reſolution of the other ar-arguments for the non-diſſolution of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/>
               <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> as it is recorded <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Recog. Beati Petri. cap.</hi> 3. (if the records be true) thus replied vpon the learned Apoſtle for the worlds immortalitie: If God be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely and only good, and the world alſo good, how ſhall God in the end deſtroy the world? If hee deſtroy that which is good, how ſhall himſelfe continue good? If hee pull it downe becauſe it is euill, how ſhall he then be free from euill, that made it euill? To which wee anſwer with <hi>S. Peter</hi> in the ſame place: That the world in its firſt origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſtate was good, yet ſo as it was foreor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined to diſſolution: nor doe wee thereby detract from Gods goodneſſe; for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens (the moſt excellent part of the world) being not made for themſelues, but for ſome end after to be reuealed; how good ſoeuer, yet were to be diſſolued, that that for which they were ordeined might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: which alſo <hi>Peter</hi> thus familiarlie ſheweth; Who ſeeth not how cunningly an egſhell is framed, yet for manifeſtation of the end of its making, it muſt be broken of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22836:45"/>neceſſitie. So muſt the preſent eſtate of the world, of neceſſitie, be deſtroyed, that the more excellent condition of the kingdome of heauen may be made manifeſt: at which time alſo this degenerated euill ſtate of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption ſhall be done away, that a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious eſtate of incorruption may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. So then, that the world ſhall haue an end, I take it, it is manifeſt; and that, not an end of annihilation, but of corruption: which indeed ſhall be a way vnto its perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Now concerning the times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the worlds diſſolution, we will not take vpon vs curiouſly to determine, ſeeing God, the beginning and end of all things, hath left the time vnreuealed vnto vs. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the means and maner of the diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Stoicks</hi> glanced at it a farre off, being of opinion, that the world ſhould by fire be diſſolued. For thinking the ſtarres and the skies fire, to haue a waſting action vpon the inferiour elements, their nouriſhing moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture by little and little decaying, when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the earth can haue refection by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor the aire procreation after its abſolute conſumption, there ſhall-remaine nothing but fire to conſume both the heauens and the earth, of which afterward a new world
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:22836:46"/>ſhould be made: whoſe opinion is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant vnto that of <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaue onely that they thought this deſtruction ſhould come of a natural neceſſity, for <hi>Peter</hi> alſo taugnt, it ſhould be by fire, wherewith <hi>God</hi> (withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hand of preſeruation) ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume this world, and of the aſhes heereof create a new; yet ſo, as neither the ſeate of the bleſſed ſouls in heauen, nor the dungeon of the damned in hell ſhould be deſtroied; that neither the iotes of the Saints, nor the torments of the wicked ſhould be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. As for the firmament and the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſpheres, together with the elements, they ſhal be indued with another &amp; that a far more excellent cnodition, putting off theſe accidents and affections of corruption fit for the continuall generation and corruption of the naturall bodies, and receiuing other qualities, agreeable to the incorruptible eſtate of the world to come; ſo that their ſubſtance ſhall be all one, howſoeuer they alter their qualities. As in the reſurrection mens bodies ſhall bee of the ſame ſubſtance, but of a different diſpoſition. <hi>For this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption muſt put on incorruption, and this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall muſt put on immortality.</hi> So that as Saint Paul ſaid, <hi>our imperfect knowledge which we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:22836:46"/>haue in this life, ſhall in the after-world be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, becauſe then we ſhall haue a morefull and perfect knowledge of God and his Chriſt.</hi> So may we well ſay this world ſhall be deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe it ſhall loſe this preſent eſtate of imperfection and put on a more glorious condition fit for the world to come. And ſo, as I take it, are thoſe places of ſcripture to bee vnderſtood, where niention is made of the worlds periſhing, that is, the preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of this world ſhall be aboliſhed, and the ſame ſubſtance indued with a more glorious condition. To which accordeth that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Pſa.</hi> 102. <hi>They ſhall periſh, but thou ſhalt indure, they ſhall all wax old as doth a garment; as a vesture ſhalt thou change them and they ſhall bee changed:</hi> plainely ſignifying, that the periſhing of the creatures ſhall be onely an alteration, which God ſhall bring vpon them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Now to that fruitleſſe queſtion of the heauens motion or reſt, we may anſwer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, that they ſhall haue an end of moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, for their motion being ordained onely for ordering things below, eſpecially for continuance of their generation, ſeeing all propagation of the ſpecies in liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as alſo mutuall procreation in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiſh
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:22836:47"/>liueleſſe bodies being ended, to what purpoſe ſhould the heauens mouing longer indure? Which may alſo ſemblably be anſwered touching the action and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the elements, as alſo for the being of things compounded of their mixture, as plants and ſenſible creatures, being things ordained onely for mans helpe, and ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, who in that bleſſed ſtate of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality without the leaſt defect ſhall neede no ſuch ſupply of his wants; which quiet &amp; reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eſtate of theſe vnder-bodies, is not, as ſome haue fondly imagined, to be attributed onely vnto the quiet reſt of the heauens; for when at the praiers of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the Sunne ſtood ſtill, and with it the reſt of the celeſtiall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, (vnleſſe we imagine the whole courſe of them to haue beene peruerted) yet cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not the naturall actions of things below, for euen at that time did <hi>Ioſhua</hi> fight? But the true cauſe of their reſt from motion is the will of the firſt cauſe, without whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuuant-fellow-working, the ſecundary cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are quite diſabled to performe their functions. From hence therefore, namely from the certainety of the worlds diſſolution we thus reaſon for our maine poſition. For if the world vncapable of eternity, haue a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:22836:47"/>limited time of endurance which it cannot paſſe, then hath man alſo his continuance bounded, at leaſt within compaſſe of the worlds laſting. For location being a thing inſeparable from exiſtence, the world, mans habitation, and manſion houſe being diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, man the principall inhabitant, muſt haue aioynt and fellow diſſolution. But for the more through-handling of this vndoubted truth, our purpoſe is more particularly to treat thereof; therefore to leaue this farre fetched, though not impertinent reaſon, taken from the worlds ineuitable deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we will come to a neerer and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per diſquiſition, holding our ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of mans owne nature.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> I haue read of a late liuing learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, <hi>Paracelſus</hi> by name, who had ſuch confidence in the abſolute perfection of his skill, that he doubted not to profeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe able by Phyſicke to preſerue a man in ſo perfect a temperature, that he ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer die by ſickneſſe: but his owne haſtie lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his life, was confutation ſufficient, of his either falſe oſtentation, or extreme madneſſe. For himſelfe either not able, which bewraied his vnskilfull impotencie, or els vnwilling, which ſhewed his wilfull
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:22836:48"/>folly, ere he came to the prime of his age, before he was thirtie yeeres old ended his daies, learning at length by his owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that arte can neuer ouercome the neceſſitie of nature; nor mans cunning pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent or preuert the decrees of the deſtinies. But to the matter in hand, the queſtion is, whether man by nature is ſubiect vnto death, the end of nature? To which we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that mans nature hath a double conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; firſt in the incorrupt ſtare and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of creation; ſecondly in the degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted condition of corruption, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were altogether vnknowen vnto the Gentiliſh Philoſophers, yet is its conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in part Philoſophicall, &amp; therefore not wholly to bee omitted. Now in the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of nature, we anſwer negatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, foraſmuch as vndefiled nature was vnca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the ſoules ſeparation from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, betweene which there was ſo abſolute and perfect an harmony and conſent, that as the vnderfaculties of the ſoule, were in ſubiection to the reaſonable and moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall part thereof, without the leaſt iarre and diſagreement; ſo fared it in the bodie, though compounded of the contrarie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the foure elements, yet ſo wel tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:22836:48"/>by proportion, that there could bee no obſeruance of the leaſt diſcord. But after that mans pride ſet abroch by the diuels ſuggeſtion, ventred to taſte of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruite for deſire of knowledge; the light of reaſon being the life of the ſoule, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt by the vnauoidable cloudes of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, there grew a diſagreement and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell among the ſubiect inferior parts of the ſoule, from whence followed the warre of the elements in the bodie, neuer to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded till the field were loſt by blood: and therefore excellent was the ſpeech of the <hi>Frier Ferus; The diſeaſes of the bodie came from ſinne the ſoules ſickneſſe, the death of the body from the death of the ſoule; and who dares ſay, the dealing is vnequall, that hee ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the death of the body, who wilfully reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the life of the ſoule? or who marueils that the diuell by Gods ſufferance tormenteth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with diſeaſes, that gaue the diuell a place of dwelling in his ſoule?</hi> ſo that the death of the bodie being the ſeparation of the ſoule from the bodie, was a puniſhment inflicted for mans wilfull ſequeſtration of himſelfe from God; and it is a good collection more then coniecturall, that the bodie had neuer beene ſubiect to the corruption of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:22836:49"/>had not the ſoule beene tainted with the corruption of defiling. Man therefore in his primarie ſtate of creation, was not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſubiect vnto death, but in the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led condition of corrupted nature, death is become ineuitable; and therefore <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Mileſius,</hi> one of the ſeuen wiſe men, was wont to ſay, that there was no difference betweene a mans life and his death, being both things agreeable vnto nature; and thence proceeded their reſolute contempt of death, becauſe they thought it was ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: whereupon the <hi>Epicure</hi> himſelfe conſidering the ineuitableneſſe of deaths comming, was (as <hi>Maximus</hi> witneſſeth) wont to ſay; <hi>that against other things we muſt finde ſome defence and remedie, onely death was vnreſiſtable: our bodie (the vndefenced citie of our ſoule) being all vnſufficient to withſtand the violent aſſaults of death.</hi> But to leaue the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite teſtimonies of the learned, grounded vpon ſo long experience, let vs deale with reaſons more artificiall, and ſhew this trueth firſt in particular, that euery man hath his endurance dated which he cannot paſſe; afterward goe vnto the ſpecies, to declare it alſo in the whole kinde.</p>
            <p>The principall and maine reaſon is taken
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:22836:49"/>from his compoſition; for man conſiſting of a matter and a forme, as doe alſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodily liuing creatures, though the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſubſtance of his ſoule be immortall, yet his body being made of the firſt matter, whoſe inſeparable companion is a deſire of change, there muſt of neceſſitie follow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; for God and nature (according to our preſuppoſition) doing nothing in vaine, this inſatiable appetite of receiuing newe formes, ſhall not finally remaine wholly fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate: if therefore we grant an induction of a new forme, we muſt withall grant an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of that that before was inherent, for as much as two formes of diuers kindes are vnſufferable together in the ſame ſubiect, whereupon doth follow the corruption of the whole compound: But if we ſhall make a more diligent and narrow inquirie into the cauſes of this diſſolution, we may find plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of reaſons miniſtred to confirme this trueth. Now the firſt cauſe naturall of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death, is contrarietie in the compound; for all corruption preſuppoſing alteration, which is onely betwixt, and by meanes of contrarie qualities, contrarietie of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent qualities, (being the onely cauſe of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration) is alſo cauſe of the compounds
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:22836:50"/>corruption, which is farther manifeſted by exprience, for ſo we ſee things wherein is leaſt diſagreement, to be of longeſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance; and the immateriall ſubſtance of the creatures ſpirituall, voide of all contrarietie, vncapable alſo of corruption; ſo that the inherence of contrarietie is one ſpecial cauſe of the compounds diſſolution. Man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe bodie conſiſts of the euer-iarring elements, <hi>Fare, Aire, Water, Earth,</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an vnreſiſtable home bred cauſe of diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. Furthermore, the conſent of al Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, and reaſon it ſelfe hath ſet downe this trueth as vndeniable, that mans life and the chiefe maintenance thereof, conſiſteth principally, if not wholly, in the due and iuſt proportionable temperature of the foure firſt qualities, <hi>Heat, Cold, Drineſſe, Moiſture,</hi> and till their diſproportion, there is no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death, or any growing ſickneſſe: whereupon <hi>Auerroes</hi> hath this definition of ſickneſſe; That <hi>it is</hi> nothing els, but <hi>the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall diſproportion of thoſe foure qualities, whereby the part whereinto the ſame is incident, is diſabled to performe its naturall functions.</hi> whereout ariſeth this collection as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, being almoſt all one with thoſe things foreſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> that the diſproportion of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:22836:50"/>foure firſt qualities, and their ſwaruing from their iuſt temperature, is cauſe of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects diſſolution: but in euerie man wee ſee a declining from his engrafted natural com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, which alſo increaſeth more and more according as his ages are altered, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mans diſſolution cannot bee auoided: where (by the way) wee muſt not let paſſe the ſaying of the Philoſopher; that <hi>mans life conſiſteth in heat,</hi> which alſo is thereby proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe in the preſence thereof, if it be not exceſſiue, we ſee a kinde of claritie and vigor as it were newly infuſed, at its depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the wonted or rather farre greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of languor. But we are not ſo to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that ſaying of the Philoſophet, as if heat were the ſole &amp; onely cauſe of life; for euen by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his own witneſſe, the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the foure firſt qualities, is the trueſt &amp; moſt proper continent cauſe of life: but the meaning is, that our naturall heate is the chiefe inſtrument of the ſoule to exerciſe the vitall functions, as <hi>nutrition, augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and ſuch like, yet ſo tempred, that it exceed not the proportionable meaſure of our naturall moiſture, the food and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our heat. And hence is that of <hi>Ficinus,</hi> that <hi>our life, as light, conſiſteth in heat,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:22836:51"/>whoſe foode and maintenance is of an aerie and fatte moiſture, not vnlike vnto oile, whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate exceſſe and impuritie or defect, are all waſters of our vitall heate;</hi> ſo that there was as great neceſſitie of moiſture as of heat in the performance of our natutall vitall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, whence came the neceſſitie of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment: for our congenerate heat hauing a conſuming action vpon our moiſture, the reſiſtance: thereof being altogether vnable to withſtand the heats aſſaulting action, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that like a kinde mother is neuer want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the neceſſities of her of ſpring, hath beſtowed on our ſoule a faculty, whereby to reſtore our decaied moiſture, through the aſſimilation of the nouriſhment applied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the waſted ſubſtance. Now the eſpeciall meanes of this decay, as is aforeſaid, is our heats aſſaulting action, whereby the ſoule continually engendreth of our humiditie, new ſpirits, for maintenance of the vitall and ſenſual actions, which being waſted by their neuer-ceaſing operation (as nothing is able long to continue without interchangable reſt) haue of neceſſitie a ſupplie from our humiditie, and our moiſture alſo equally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied, hath the like ſupply made by nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which wee receiue, leſt there ſhould
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:22836:51"/>follow a ſudden deſtruction: hence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that is from the neceſſitie of continuall nouriſhment, we inferre a decay of naturall moiſture, for otherwiſe whereunto is nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion directed?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> But heere remaineth a doubt; for if there be reſtitution of the loſt naturall moiſture, made by the receipt of nouriſhment, whence commeth death the end of nature? for our heat hauing alway what to feede vpon, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by nature or by this outward ſupply of nouriſhment, and death neuer aſſailing vs, but by the baniſhment and extinguiſhing of this naturall heate, where is this neceſſity of ending our life? The anſwer is, that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity of the outward nouriſhment inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied, by degrees tainteth that naturall ingendred humidity, and by its continuall mixture at length wholly corrupteth it. For as in the mingling of water with wine, the greater the infuſion of water is, the more is the infeebling and weakening of the wines force, till at length it be cleane oppreſſed and extinguiſhed: ſo is it in the caſe of nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, wherein though at firſt our naturall heat and moiſture retaine their purity and naturall quality, yet at length by continuall mixture of the alimentary humor, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22836:52"/>a totall and perfect corruption of their integrity. Now if by the reſtoratiue faculty of the ſoule there could bee ſupplie made of as pure moiſture as that which was loſt, the creature might (for any thing in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) be preferued aliue for euer. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ficinus</hi> beſide the iuſt proportion of moiſture vnto the heat, requireth alſo purity and incorruption in the moiſture, for as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie moiſture is not a preſeruer of the light of a lampe, but though oile maintaines the flame, yet water doth quench it: ſo is it in the caſe of our life which principally conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in heat, for the watriſh humidity doth cleane extinguiſh it. And thence it is that old men when they are neereſt vnto their end abound with a watriſh humour, yet are they ſaid to be cold and dry, as wanting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that moiſture which is the fitteſt for their heat to feed vpon.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> So that the truth of the poſition is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the particulars, namely that euery man hath an end and tearme of indurance which he cannot paſſe. Now this end commeth either by meanes naturall and growing in him, or by violent and vnnaturall meanes. Whereupon they haue diſtinguiſhed death into two kinds, one <hi>Naturall,</hi> the other <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent:</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:22836:52"/>Naturall death is where our natiue moiſture is by meanes of our haturall heat (continually working vpon it) conſumed &amp; diſpatched, whence followeth a lingring, languiſhing and pining of our naturall heate as wanting what to feed vpon; contrary to the ſubtile opinion of the fault-finding <hi>Iulius Scaliger,</hi> that thought our naturall heat to be weakned, and in the end cleane conſumed onely by want of interchangeable reſt, and ceaſing from its operation. For as we ſee fire not waſted by much vſe, but lingringly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed by decay and want of fit fewell for to feed vpon; ſo our home-bred naturall heat not tired with ouer-working, but lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing with the decay of fit food, is at length together with our moiſture its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall prouided foode, cleane conſumed. To which may be added that ſaying of <hi>Fernelius</hi> to this purpoſe, that though <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> himſelfe, the God of <hi>Phyſicke</hi> had the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the moſt temperate complexioned man that can be imagined, and that from his birth, to keepe him from all outward annoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances whatſoeuer, yet hath he in himſelfe an home-bred enemy by little and little to ſpoile him of his life. Vnnaturall and violent death, is when our naturall heat either with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22836:53"/>too much cold, or exceſſiue externall heat, or with an immoderate meaſure of moiſture is extinguiſhed. According to which two kinds of death, the learned School-men haue deuiſed a double tearme of our life: There is, ſay they, <hi>A tearme of nature,</hi> and there is, <hi>A tearme beſide nature. The naturall tearme,</hi> is that vtmoſt time, that a man by his complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion can reach vnto, whch is farther off or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer according to the differences of mens temperatures. The <hi>terme</hi> or limit <hi>beſide na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is when mans life either commeth ſhort of that length which by his complexion hee may attaine vnto, or is protracted and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed beyond the courſe of nature, &amp; that they cal the end or terme of Gods <hi>preſcience,</hi> &amp; fore-appointment in his vnreaueled will, which a man can neither preuent, nor yet prolong: and this hath for the moſt part place in violent death; and was therefore alſo propounded by thoſe deuout Schoole-men, leſt men ſhould not thinke they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended only vpon chance, or fell out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods eſpeciall counſell and diſpoſing. For ſo we ſee in daily experience, many men in the prime of their yeeres and ſtrength of their age, either by riot, or famine, peſtilence or ſword, ſuddenly cut off, and we are many
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:22836:53"/>times mooued with pity in that behalfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing their eſtate that in our iudgements might haue liued a great deale longer: as indeed they might, if we reſpect what they were capable of by their complexion; but in regard of Gods decree and purpoſe it was impoſſible for them to paſſe that moment and point of time: for Gods preſcience can neuer be deceiued. And this, to auoid tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, may briefly ſerue for the certainetie of the end of particular men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> Now for the indurance of man in <hi>ſpecie</hi> (in which regard onely he is ſaid to be a part of the world) we may paſſe ouer vnto it by way of <hi>Prolepſis,</hi> or preoccupation. For it may be obiected, that though there is a limited endurance of particular and ſingle men, yet there may be a perpetuall preſeruation of the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or kinde: and therefore God hath beſtowed on man a faculty of procreation to propagate his kinde; that though euery man muſt (of a naturall neceſſity) die, yet might hee leaue an other of his owne kinde behinde him, that ſo there might be a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall and euerlaſting ſucceſſion. To which we anſwer, that if they grant a corruption in the particular, they muſt withall grant it in the <hi>ſpecies.</hi> For the <hi>ſpecies</hi> being a thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22836:54"/>onely in imagination, not hauing any reall being, but as wee conceiue of it in the particulars, it is a neceſſary illation, that from the corruption of all the particulars, we may conclude the like of the generall. But to ſhew it more plainely, by a demonſtratiue proceeding, we may obſerue the like courſe of decay in the <hi>ſpecies</hi> as there is in the <hi>indiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duum.</hi> For as nutrition is to the particular, ſo is generation to the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> in the caſe of their continuance and preſeruation: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as by the nouriſhment we take for reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our naturall moiſture, there being ſupplied not ſo pure humidity as was loſt, the particulars decaying by little and little, are at laſt cleane conſumed: ſo by procreation, the maintenace of our <hi>ſpecies,</hi> the purity of our complexion being by degrees and by time diminiſhed, at length there followes, euen of neceſſitie, an abſolute corruption. Now (as I conceiue of it) the decay commeth thus, for the particulars, whoſe function this generation is, being by continuall mixture of outward nouriſhment corrupted, the ſeed, the matter and means of propagation cannot but be tainted with like corruption. And that is the chiefe reaſon amongſt other leſſe principall, that men in this age of the world
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:22836:54"/>are of leſſe continuance than they were in former time. From all which we thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; if the naturall vigour of the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> be by little and little continually weakened, there muſt of neceſſity in the end follow a full and perfect corruption. For (as <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> ſaid of the diuiſion of any thing finite, that by often detraction, though but of a little quantity, the whole becommeth at length vncapable of diuiſion) ſo by continuall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the vertue of the kinde, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth at length euen of neceſſity, a totall and ineuitable extinguiſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> Now to that friuolous fruitleſſe queſtion, whether this end and deſtruction be of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or proceedeth from any effectual ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God; wee may thus anſwer: that we diſpute not what ſhall be in this caſe, but what may bee: and according to that ſenſe wee ſay, that euen of ai naturall neceſſitie (though God ſhould not vntimely cut off the thred of our life) yet euen of its owne accord, ſhould whole mankind haue an end; which is manifeſt by that forenamed continuall curtalling of our life, obſerued by experience, and noted out of the legends of antiquities: for before that vniuerſall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge in <hi>Noahs</hi> time, we reade of ſome that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:22836:55"/>liued, ſix, ſeuen, eight, nine hundred yeeres; as <hi>Adam, Noah, Methuſalem,</hi> and others. After the floud, he that liued longeſt, recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in holy hiſtorie, exceeded not the age of a hundred and twentie yeeres: ſome few yeeres after, in <hi>Dauids</hi> time, it fell to ſeuentie yeeres, or if there were any ouerplus, it was mingled with labour and ſorrow, more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the name of death than life. So that we may hence conclude, that it is impoſſible for mankinde to laſt for euer, hauing inwardly in his nature ſufficient and vnpreuentable cauſes of diſſolution.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus euidenced the truth of our two poſitions, that there is a ſet time of endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance vnto euery man and vnto all mankind, and learning by experience, the naturall and true mother of knowledge, that among the particulars ſo me haue a longer, ſome a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time of continuance, and that euen by nature; it remaineth that with all poſſible breuity and perſpicuity, wee ſet downe the cauſes naturall of this naturall difference, which we can no otherwiſe doe, than by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the receiued cauſes of the length and ſhortneſſe of mans life, and according as they are more or leſſe in any man, ſo iudge of their effects. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (in his preface to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:22836:55"/>this treatiſe) premiſeth a word or two touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diuers conſideration of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence according to the diuerſity of that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto which they are incident. For in theſe tearms, of <hi>length,</hi> and <hi>ſhortneſſe</hi> of life, we may compare either things of the ſame kinde, as man with man, or things of diuers kinds, as reaſonable creatures with liueleſſe &amp; ſenſible things; for there are ſome vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures longer liued then man, for ſo <hi>Heſiodus</hi> reporteth of the Crow, that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth out nine mens liues (meaſuring euerie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be 100 yeeres) the Hart, by the ſame aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors witneſſe, thriſe as many: the Rauen trebleth the Harts endurance: and thence was that plaint of dying <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> and complaint of natures inequality &amp; as it were blindfolded diſpoſition of her benefits, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this kinde, that to <hi>Harts</hi> and <hi>Crowes</hi> ſo thankleſly had giuen ſo long time of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, which was denied vnto man, that could and would haue better imploied that benefit. Which complaint was perſonally renewed and aggrauated by <hi>Bewaldus,</hi> an old <hi>Grammarian,</hi> for the ſticks not in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome captious Atheiſt to expoſtulate the matter with God, why our life (in theſe times) is ſo curtalled, that for the many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22836:56"/>of yeeres which in the firſt age of the world men liued, wee haue our ſtint and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits within the compaſſe of little more than halfe an hundred? But <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his firſt booke of <hi>Antiquties,</hi> giueth theſe reaſons, and firſt of all the wholeſome goodneſſe of their nouriſhment, and the outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing elements which they inhabited. For their corrupted nature was not greedily ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with deſire of their corruptions increaſe as headlongly &amp; on the ſudden to engulfe it ſelfe into all extremity, but by degrees and lingringly, as vpon conſtraint by little and little deſcendeth from that top &amp; perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of corruption. And as euery thing was neereſt vnto that beginning, ſo was it cleereſt and leſſe tainted with corruption. We ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the laſt age and exteremity of the world, are in a more extreame degree of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption by reaſon of that frequent alteration in the elements when euery mutation ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſomewhat to the begun impurity. A ſecond reaſon was Gods wil &amp; bountifulnes, the benefit whereof was not bounded in that ſmall compaſſe and limit of time, but exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo vnto vs and to our poſterity. For God therfore granted them a longer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, for reuealing of many hidden my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:22836:56"/>eſpecially in Aſtrologie; for the courſe of many of the celeſtiall bodies could neuer haue bene learned, no not ſo much as in any mediocrity, had not God giuen ſome of them at leaſt ſix hundred yeeres to liue in, in which time, the great yeere as they call it, is fulfilled and perfected. To which wee may adde the fewneſſe of the earths inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in the beginning of the world, God preuenting the diſpeopling of the new world, and prouiding for its ſtore and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhing. And yet (if we beleeue <hi>Anacro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> I know not how credible a witneſſe being a Poet) within theſe few ages laſt paſt, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganthonius</hi> king of the <hi>Tarteſſians,</hi> liued an hundred and fiftie yeeres; <hi>Cinyras</hi> of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> an hundred and ſixtie yeeres; <hi>Eginus</hi> two hundred; and as <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Cornelius</hi> report, there was one in <hi>Illyrium</hi> called <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that liued the full and complet terme of ſix hundred yeeres; and <hi>Xenophon</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of one, who in the ile of the <hi>Latines,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued eight hundred yeeres. But I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with <hi>Pliny,</hi> that it is very vnlikely, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it may bee that they erred in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, not knowing how according to diuerſitie of nations in former ages, there were manifold and ſundry meaſures of the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:22836:57"/>yeares; for the old Arcadians made foure yeeres of one of ours, allotting vnto euerie yeere three moneths. The Egyptians made as many yeeres as moneths, according to the Moones finiſhed and renewed courſe: and according vnto this reckoning, it will be no ſtrange thing, that a man ſhould euen in theſe daies liue a thouſand yeeres. But not to proſecute the diuers continuance of things in diuers kindes, as alſo to let paſſe the farther examination of the decaied eſtate of mans life, leſt wee againe reuiue the now quenched fire of godleſſe indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at the ſhortneſſe of our life, we wil come to the moſt pertinent compariſon of man with man in this kinde, if firſt we ſhall onely remember what was <hi>Plinies</hi> opinion of the ſhortning our liues, namely, that God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in did greatly gratifie vs, by cutting off theſe daies of miſerie: agreeable to which, <hi>Silemus</hi> being demanded what was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt happineſſe and good that God could doe a man, made anſwer, <hi>Neuer to be borne;</hi> and the next vnto that, <hi>to die quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But touching the cauſes of long life, wee may thus brieflie dichotomiſe them, for they are either inward or outward; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſes are ſuch as either we haue natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:22836:57"/>ingrafted, or els gotten by arte, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie &amp; wiſdome: that of nature is the good temperature and proportionate mixture of the foure firſt qualities in the body; for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate heat that is vnproportionate to the quantitie of moiſture, rather haſtneth death by the too ſpeedie conſumption of its moiſt food, than any way prolongeth life, as we ſee in men of cholericke conſtitution. So alſo, too great colde, that is ouerſwaying the quantity or vertue of our natural heat, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth our life: and thence it is that old men the neerer they draw vnto their ends, haue their bodies ouergrowen with cold: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon all the Aſtrologians haue obſerued <hi>Saturne</hi> to be a Planet enemie vnto life, as hauing a vertue of cold and drought, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly (as ſome imagine) was he painted with a ſithe in his hand, cutting downe as it were and killing men with the operation and infuſion of theſe two deadly qualities: which may alſo be ſaid of the exceſſe of the other two contrarie qualities, moiſture and drought; for too much moiſture oppreſſeth the naturall heat, as wee ſee greene-wood quench an vnequall quantitie of fire: and thence it is, that willowes and ſuch like, whoſe almoſt naturall place is the riuers
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:22836:58"/>ſide, are of ſhort continuance, becauſe their too much &amp; too wateriſh moiſture drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their heat. So that hereby (as I take it) it is manifeſt, that none of theſe qualities ſingly and by themſelues, are true cauſes of long life, but iointly all in a good and iuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion.</p>
            <p>Now if any man ſhall (out of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) obiect, that the two qualities of life, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>moiſture,</hi> are onely cauſes of long life: we may anſwer, that theſe two by themſelues procure not length of life, but in a certain meaſure &amp; proportion. Now the rebater of the heats too too actiue qualitie, is his contrarie, cold; and the <hi>moderatour</hi> &amp; <hi>temperer</hi> of the moiſtures acceſſe is drought: ſo that in euery man the foure firſt qualities are requiſite; yet were two onely mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> as being thoſe onely which directly cauſe long life; the other two one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incluſiuely ſet downe, as being no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe effectually profitable for life, than as they temper and abate the exceſſe of the two principall. But becauſe euery moiſture is not cauſe of life, nor the beſt moiſture in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery quantity, there are one or two requiſite conditions annexed: firſt concerning the qualitie, that it be not too thinne and fluid,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:22836:58"/>ſuch as is the naturall diſpoſition of water; but more cleauing and fat, ſuch as may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the nature of oile, for its better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation from putrefaction: ſecondly, that it haue ſome competent degree of heat, to keepe it from congealing; laſt of all, that it be pure, not mingled with excrementall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities; foraſmuch as all mixture of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities is againſt nature, enemie to good digeſtion, and ſound nutrition. Thoſe things thus obſerued, our moiſture ſhall be ſufficiently qualified for our liues mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Touching the quantitie, in a word, (as is before ſaid) it muſt neither bee exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue, leſt the too great quantitie oppreſſe our heat, as wee ſee infuſion of too much oile oftentimes put out the lampe; nor yet defectiue, leſt the deuouring action of our heat, too ſoone conſume it: but in a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent mediocrity, ſuch as the heat may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ouer-haſtily vanquiſh, nor with the violence of exceſſiue inequalitie too ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be extinguiſhed. Where briefly wee may ſee the reaſon, why man is longer liued than other creatures of more vaſt bodies; for though in the large capacitie of their great receiuers, they haue a greater quantity of this naturall moiſture than is incident
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:22836:59"/>vnto mans ſmall body, yet haue they it not ſo well tempered and proportioned to their heat, which may well bee gathered by their ſlowe and ſeldome breathing. So that it is true which the Philoſopher hath, that the great or little quantitie of the bodie, is no ſufficient cauſe of long life. And yet this is withall moſt true, that where there is greateſt ſtore of humiditie with a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent proportion of heat, there is greateſt fitneſſe naturally for long life. And that is the reaſon why thoſe that in their infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie are moſt ſubiect to a languiſhing diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, are afterward moſt healthfull, and for the moſt part longeſt liued. For the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of their naturall moiſture hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth the too ſpeedy preuailing of the heat, by reſiſting its action: and ſo is it the leſſe mingled with forren impurities. For as we ſee the Smiths fire, by the moderate ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of water, though at firſt for a time its force is ſomewhat abated, yet it at length ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouercome its weake aduerſary, as in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph burneth the cleerer, and laſteth lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; ſo fareth it in our bodies: for our heat not able on the ſudden to ouerſway our multitude of moiſture, is the longer hindred from conſuming it, whence proceedeth long
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:22836:59"/>life, and after it hath gotten the vpper hand, performeth with more facility its naturall functions, whence commeth healthfulneſſe; where wee may alſo explane that <hi>Probleme,</hi> why children that are too ripe witted in their childhood, are for the moſt part either ſhorteſt liued, or els toward their old age moſt ſottiſh, according to our Prouerbe; <hi>Soone ripe, ſoone rotten:</hi> for hence wee may gather, that from the beginning they had but little moiſture, ouer which their heat ſoone preuailed; for much humiditie is cauſe of blockiſhneſſe and folly: whence is that of <hi>Galen,</hi> that <hi>fleame being a cold wateriſh humour, is of no force for ornament of good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions:</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> doubted not to ſay, that looke how much moiſture there is in vs, ſo much alſo is our folly; and thereof it is, as the ſame <hi>Plato</hi> obſerueth, that children and women are for the moſt part moſt fooliſh. For the glorious light and Sunne-like ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of the ſoule, is therwith as with a cloud obſcured and intercepted, which is an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent proofe of the ſmall ſtore of moiſture in theſe quicke witted forward children, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which the heat ſo much the ſooner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining dominion, and in proceſſe of time drying the braine, the ſubordinate inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:22836:60"/>of vnderſtanding, either quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroieth it, and ſo bringeth death, or els ſo corrupts it, that it is altogether vnable and vnfit to ſteed the inner ſenſes in their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, whereon the vnderſtanding in this priſon of the boby principally dependeth: which may no leſſe fitly ſerue for anſwer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that conſequent demand, why thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants for the moſt part are ſooneſt able to walke, to talke, to conceiue, to remember, and ſuch like; the reaſon is taken from the little quantitie of moiſture; which may bee gathered by the contrary diſpoſition in the otherwiſe affected ſubiects, as alſo by that which we ſee in daily experience in creatures of other kinds. For whereas man by reaſon of his fluid, vnſetled ſubſtance, hath for the better ſtrengthning of his ioints his bodie ſwathed, and is a long time before he is able to ſtand or walke, or performe any ſuch like his vitall functions; we ſee other creatures almoſt in the ſame moment, borne and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſtand, walke, and ſuch like; for their vnequall quantitie of heat, preuailing ouer the little ſtore of moiſture, ſoone ſitteth them for the performance of vitall actions, that being the ſoules chiefe inſtrument in the diſcharge of her duties. Now if any man
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:22836:60"/>ſhall aske what this iuſt proportion is, and when they are tempred ſo as may beſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable for long life, the anſwer is, that heat and moiſture are then well proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned when neither the moiſture with its too great quantity deuoureth the heat, nor the ouermuch heat, too ſuddenlie conſumes and eateth vp the moiſture. Yet muſt the heat haue a kind of dominion ouer the moiſture, elſe can it not be able to nouriſh the bodie. For in nutrition the thing nouriſhed, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the inſtrument ordained for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, muſt actually worke vpon that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is nouriſhed. And becauſe that euery Agent muſt be proportioned vnto the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in the inequality of exceſſe, therefore muſt the heat being the ſoules ſole actiue inſtrument of nutrition, haue dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the moiſture, the ſubiect matter of that facultie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> Touching the complexions, the queſtion is, which of them is beſt diſpoſed and fitted for length of life. To take that for granted which <hi>Fernelius</hi> doubteth of, namely, that there are foure, if not onely yet chiefely, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table complexions; we anſwer that thoſe of a ſanguine conſtitution are by nature capable of the longeſt life; as hauing the two quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:22836:61"/>of life beſt tempred. And therefore is compared vnto the aire, which is moderatly hot and in the higheſt degree moiſt. Yet not with that too thinne and fluid watriſh moiſture, but more oily; oile it ſelfe reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the true nature of the aire. Therefore the ſanguine complexion is fitteſt for long life. For choler is an humor like vnto fire, extreame hot and moderatly drie, and ſo vnſufficient to make ſupply of moiſture to the deuouring operation of that firie heat, which is in it. In the flegmaticke the copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of that humour reſembling water, oppreſſeth the heat and ſo hindreth good digeſtion, whence proceed crudities in the ſtomacke and liuer, from whence they are diffuſed into the veines, and ſo vnto all the parts of the body, and at length the body is ouergrowen with corruption. Laſtly, melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly reſembling the earth and its qualities, cold and drought, both enemies to life, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth the deſtruction of the body where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it is incident.</p>
            <p>The ſecond inward cauſe of long life is, the moderation of our affections. Whether it be that naturall <hi>appetite</hi> of <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drinke</hi> for nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or thoſe other of <hi>anger, loue, ioy, luſt, ſorrow,</hi> and ſuch like. For all theſe are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:22836:61"/>auaileable both waies, either in exceſſe to kill, or in moderation to ſaue. Touching the moderate vſe of meats and drinkes, what neede we ſeeke farre for proofe of its profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablenes to preſerue life, when we ſee ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daily by ſurfetting &amp; ouercharging their ſtomacks with too much and too riotus vſe of meats, vntimely end their daies: and contrariwiſe, men very craſie and ſickely by temperancie and moderation many times protract their liues almoſt to an incredible length? For ſo is it reported of one <hi>Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> a ſtudent in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his daies, the moſt weake and ſickely of any that liued in that time by the teſtimony both of <hi>Plato</hi> &amp; of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle;</hi> who notwithſtanding, by his diligent care and guidance of himſelfe liued full out 100. yeeres; and no maruell, for ſo did he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the daily decay of his humidity, by ſupply of nouriſhment, and neither ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed his heat, with the abundance of moiſture, nor mingled his radicall moiſture with too much externall ſuperfluous impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Where we may reſolue that doubt, how it comes to paſſe, <hi>that often drinkers of wine for the moſt part haſten their death;</hi> The reaſon is, that the vehement heat of the wine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth their moiſture, and ſo by detraction
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:22836:62"/>of the heats food, in time alſo extinguiſheth the heat. Now if any man ſhall require me to preſcribe a diet vnto him; though I be no Phyſitian, yet will I referre him vnto that of the excellent Emperour, who neuer eat till he was hungry, nor euer proceeded to a glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatiety. For the extreames are dangerous both <hi>exceſſe</hi> and <hi>defect;</hi> too much meate hindring good digeſtion and ingendring crudities, &amp; too little giuing occaſion of the heats too ſudden preuailing ouer the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, both which are friends of death: Not would I counſell men ſtrictly to tie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto ſet houres; for that, ſaith <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> is dangerous, cauſing many times, either delaie of applying nouriſhment, or too ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy miniſtring before the former digeſtion is finiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> And heere we may ſeaſonably annex the vſe of exerciſe, for that is a thing very auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to digeſtion; diſperſing the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into the parts of the body, and being (as it were) the bellowes to kindle and reuiue our naturall heate: for ouermuch reſt and ceaſing from motion cooleth the body. And as the elementiſh fire which we vſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it bee ſometime blowen and fed as it were with aire is extinguiſhed: ſo our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:22836:62"/>heat without exerciſe and motion is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort caſt on ſleep, or rather benummed, whence proceedeth that other daughter of dulneſſe, <hi>collection of excremental ſuperfluities,</hi> the heat being not able to digeſt our recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nouriſhment; &amp; thence is that corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and rottenneſſe which ouertaketh theſe ſlow-backes; as we ſee ſtanding water ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt putrifie and gather filth. Wherefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> enquiring the cauſes of the <hi>toile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome trauell of ſome women in child-birth ouer others,</hi> ſetteth down this as principall among the reſt, namely their idleneſſe and want of exerciſe; for his experience of women in other countries ſo accuſtomed to paines ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, had taught him; for to them child-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring was not ſo painefull, their labour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming thoſe excrements that are the vſuall impediments of eaſe in that kinde. Nor will I take vpon me to limit any man to any kind of exerciſe rather than an other, or appoint any time; although this caueat will not be amiſſe preſcribed, that they vſe not to ſtirre themſelues more violently than is ordinary, before the through digeſtion of meate; for then they clogge their ſtomacks and make them vnfit for after concoction, and withall fill their bodies with raw humours, which by
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:22836:63"/>exerciſe are diſperſed through the veines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al the parts of the body: onely as inother things, ſo eſpecially in exerciſe of what kinde ſoeuer, either for delight, or of paines, let them remember <hi>moderation,</hi> that it be neither too much, nor to little. Not too much, that is, neither too vehement, nor yet continual, but interchangeable, for both theſe by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming of the ſpirits, are alike hurtfull; not too little, for continued reſt and idleneſſe (as is afore ſaid) engendreth putrefaction. Where the conſideration of the moderate vſe of ſleepe and waking is very incident, for they are both things neceſſary for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of life in their mediocrity, both as hurtfull if beyond meaſure. For immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and vnſeaſonable watching waſteth the ſpirits, and by conſuming of the vitall iuice, cauſeth leanneſſe in the body, enfeebleth the parts thereof, hindreth the operation of the ſenſes, drieth the marrow and the braine: inſomuch that oftentimes it proceedeth to doting and frenſie. So likewiſe too much ſleepe hindreth our health and well-fare by looſing the parts of the body, dulling the naturall heat, conſuming the moiſture, and ſuch like. But moderatly vſed and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably they are notable meanes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:22836:63"/>and preſeruing health, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this varietie and change is verie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſome and refreſhing, but much more by reſtoring or hindring the decay of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> Now touching theſe other affections, as <hi>anger, ioie, ſorrow</hi> and ſuch like, though wee read not of many that haue ſuddenly died for anger, yet by reaſon of that ſudden emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of hear into the outward parts of the body, and kindling as it were the fire of cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, it muſt needs be very hurtful, when as all ſuddenneſſe, eſpecially ioyned with vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, is an horror vnto nature. And cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler inflameth the blood, whence proceedeth that vnreaſonableneſſe &amp; raging, vſually ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in men ouermuch angred. But exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are plentifull of ſuch as with ſudden and immoderat ioy haue died; as <hi>Pliny</hi> reports of <hi>Sophocles</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that immediately vpon tidings of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory gaue vp the ghoſt. And <hi>Liuie</hi> maketh mention of two mothers at Rome, that after the bloudy battell of <hi>Cannas,</hi> for ioie of the ſafe and vnexpected returne of their ſonnes, ſuddenly fell downe dead: the one meeting her ſonne at the City gate, the other in her houſe bewayling the reported death of her
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:22836:64"/>ſonne, when on the ſudden beſide her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, ſafely preſented himſelfe to her ſight. The like alſo <hi>Gellius</hi> writeth of one <hi>Dingenes</hi> of Rhodes, that hauing his three ſons, for the maſtery obtained at the games, in one day crowned, after his ſonnes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements and the peoples applauſe, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly yeelded vp the ghoſt. The meanes of this death was the ſudden dilatation of the heart, the vitall ſpirits and the heat whoſe beginning is the heart, being too farre caried from their fountaine. So alſo read wee of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that not able to finde the reaſon why <hi>Euripus,</hi> (a part of the ſea ſituated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Aulis</hi> of <hi>Bootia</hi> and <hi>Eubaea</hi>) ebbed &amp; flowed ſeuen times a day, for very greefe died: the means and maner of his death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the too great contraction of the ſpirits, whereby the heat was as it were with ſmoke chaoked. The like is reported of <hi>Diodorus</hi> a logician, who for ſhame that he could not at the firſt anſwer the trifling queſtion which <hi>Stilpo</hi> put out, ſuddenly ended his daies. Which is alſo written of <hi>Homer,</hi> who in the Ile <hi>Ios</hi> ſitting on the ſea ſhore, demanded of the fiſher-men if they had taken any thing, they thus obſcurely in riddle-wiſe made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwer; <hi>Thoſe that we tooke we left behind, thoſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:22836:64"/>that we could not catch, we bring with us.</hi> For in the ſun-ſhine (as they ſay it is ſhipmens fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions) they made inquiſition for their back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting familiars, and ſome they tooke, and cruelly preſſed vnto death, leauing their liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe carcaſes to bee deuoured of the fiſhes: thoſe that craftily had inſinuated themſelues either into their fleſh, or into the inſide of their apparrell, they were faine to bring away with them. But quicke witted <hi>Homer,</hi> not able on the ſudden to expound this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme, for ſhame, (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Herodotus</hi> write of him) gaue vp the ghoſt. For the ſpirits and blood (as in all kinde of feare it falleth out) retiring to the inward parts, as to a tower of defence, by their ſudden retrait, and reuerberation, redouble the heate and ſo inflaming the heart, not able to be cooled againe by reſpiration, ſtifles the patient.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> Concerning Venery, deaths beſt harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I ſhall not neede to recite the infinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of them, that by meanes therof haue haſtened their deaths, nor indeed is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to number thoſe innumerable troops that through luſt either before the actuall accompliſhment, or after the too frequent ſatisfying the ſame haue ended their youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full daies. It was well ſaid of one, that <hi>Venus
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:22836:65"/>prouideth not for thoſe that are already borne, but for thoſe that ſhalbe borne,</hi> and therefore <hi>Auicenna,</hi> a learned <hi>Philoſopher</hi> &amp; <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> doubted not to ſay, that the emiſſion of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſeed more than the body could well beare was a great deale more hurtfull than the loſſe of fortie times ſo much blood. For it wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the ſpirits, weakeneth the ſtomack, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebleth and drieth vp the braine and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, whereby eſpecially it haſtneth death. And the truth heereof <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> prooueth by his experimentall obſeruation, for ſo hath he noted the cocke-ſparow by immoderate and too frequent vſe of Venery, very ſeldome to liue out the tearme of two yeeres, and the ſame reaſon hee giueth why the Mule a mixt creature begotten betweene an horſe &amp; an aſſe is longer liued, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either of them, for his inſting in that kinde, is but once only through the whole courſe of his life. To which we may adde the diuerſity of the ſex, for the male according vnto <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie kinde almoſt, is by nature better fitted for long life than the female, hauing greater force of heat, and the moiſture more firm &amp; better able to reſiſt than the fluid ſubſtance of the female; and thence it is that women for the moſt part are ſooner perfected than
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:22836:65"/>men, being ſooner fit for generation, ſooner in the flower and prime of their age, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, ſooner old, for their heat though lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, yet ſooner preuaileth ouer that fluid thinne ſubſtance and moiſture of theirs, than it poſſibly can ouer that ſolid and compact humiditie which is in man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> But leſt our Treatiſe grow too big, we wil proceed to thoſe other outward cauſes of long life, ſuch as bee the influences of the Stars, either in our conception and birth, or in the country &amp; ſoile wherin we liue, as alſo the goodneſſe of the ſoile it ſelfe, both of the earth &amp; aire. For though it be true that the celeſtiall bodies haue no direct action either of inclination or conſtraint vpon the reaſonable ſoule of man, which is immateri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, yet is it as true that they haue ſingular and eſpeciall operations vpon our bodies; for ſo wee ſee the fruitfulneſſe and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the earth depends vpon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens good and bad aſpect; the ſea followes the motion and alteration of the Moone, the yeere diſtinguiſhed into its foure parts, according to the acceſſe or farther abſence of the Sun; and therefore <hi>Galen,</hi> the father of Phyſitians, counſelled his ſcholers to haue eſpeciall reſpect vnto the coniunction
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:22836:66"/>of the Planets in their ſignes, whenſoeuer they vndertake any cure: and, which is more fit for the preſent purpoſe, the Aſtrologers haue aſſigned vnto euery Planet a monthly dominion ouer the childe conceiued in the wombe, according to their order and ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The firſt moneth is allotted vnto <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne:</hi> the ſecond vnto <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and ſo foorth in order, vntill they haue all finiſhed their dominion, and then they begin againe: which is the eſpeciall reaſon alleaged by ſome, why the childe that is borne in the eight moneth, for the moſt part dieth, when as oftentimes thoſe that are brought foorth a moneth ſooner or later, liue in verie good health: for <hi>Saturne</hi> is a planet whoſe influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cauſeth colde and drineſſe, which both are qualities enemies vnto life. Now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the laſt, though not the leaſt cauſe of long life, and that is the goodneſſe of the ſoile, and wholeſomneſſe of the aire: for it is ſo recorded in Hiſtories, and approoued by the teſtimonie of our late trauellers, that in that part of <hi>India</hi> which is called <hi>Oner,</hi> the inhabitants are very long liued, and for the moſt part very healthfull, inſomuch that many of them liue vntill they bee aboue an hundred yeeres old; and wee ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:22836:66"/>in our country, how perilous not onely peſtilent aire is, but euen the vnholeſomnes of the fennie countries, that are often anoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſtinking and vnſauorie fogges. <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> in his treatiſe of the length and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, maketh choice of a hot coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as fitteſt for preſeruation and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of life; for ſo he obſerueth it, that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents bred and brought vp in hot coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, are generally bigger bodied then thoſe that are found in colder climets: and thoſe fiſhes that breed in the red ſea, are alſo lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than thoſe in the ſeas which are not ſo hot, and that, though they bee of the ſame kinde; which is a manifeſt proofe of their longer continuance: els how commeth it to paſſe, that they haue greater growth? and againe, thoſe creatures that liue in cold climets, haue a more wateriſh kinde of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and fitter for congelation; whence followeth the ſpeedier deſtruction of the inhabitants: but the trueth is, that neither hot countries, nor colder climets, are of themſelues any furtherance vnto long life, for thoſe that are of a cholericke fierie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, liue longer in cold countries, and ſuch as be of colder complexion, liue beſt and longeſt in hot regions, but according
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:22836:67"/>to the diuerſitie of mens complexions, ſo liue they better or worſe in diuers countries. Thoſe that are too hot of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution, by my counſell, ſhall make choice of a country in ſome meaſure and degrees cold, leſt the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward heat of the circumiacent aire increaſe the fire within, and make it more vehement; and thence is it that thoſe in the hotteſt part of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> are ſhorteſt liued, hauing that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall exceſſe of heat ſet on fire with the acceſſe of the externall heat of the aire. Now for ſuch as abound with too much moiſture, their beſt habitation in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is in hot and drie regions, that the heat and drought of the ſoile may abate the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of the humor. But there are ſome of a moderate and well proportioned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and if any man ſhall aske what country is beſt for them to dwel in, I anſwer, that there are two ſorts of men thus tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; ſome are of a more weake and leſſe hardy diſpoſition, and to them I would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a dwelling in countries rather hot then cold, that the heat of the place may comfort and ſtrengthen the heate of their bodies. Others againe are more hardy &amp; better able to indure any not extreame violence of cold; and for them it is beſt to liue in colder cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:22836:67"/>for ſo is their heat better inabled to performe it functions of digeſtion and ſuch like; and therefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Politicks ſaith; that Northren men, and generally ſuch as dwell in colder countries, are ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and bigger bodied, and moſt an end better couraged, and longer liued: for the coldneſſe of the compaſſing aire, reflects the heat into the inward parts; and by that reflexion, the heats force is increaſed, and the parts gathered better and cloſer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which both further the performance of its duties. And that is the reaſon why men in Winter are more hungry and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring than in Summer, as experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs all: for the ſtomacke is ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the heats compreſſion, to the better concocting of the receiued nouriſhment. Thus therefore may wee conclude with the expoſition of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his opinion in this caſe, when he ſaith, that hot places are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for long life, in his booke of the <hi>Length and ſhortneſſe of mans life;</hi> and in his Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, <hi>The inhabitants of colder climates, are ſtronger and longer liued:</hi> for thus may we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile this apparent contradiction: that for men of more cold complexions, hot places are moſt preſeruatiue and healthfull;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:22836:68"/>and for the contrary complexioned men, contrary affected places; ſo that, if two of the ſame conſtitution (imagine them both to be hot) liue, the one in a cold, the other in an hot region (if their heat was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly proportioned to their moiſture, but vnequally in the exceſſe) he that made choiſe of the colder habitation, prouided beſt for his life. And thus haue we briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſet downe the common-receiued cauſes of long life, where-out by the conſequence of contraries wee may deduce the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſhort life. And they are, firſt the ſmall quantity and watriſhneſſe of the moiſture. Secondly, the ſuperfluous abundance of excrements. Thirdly, the badneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holeſomeneſſe of the ſoile. Fourthly, the vngentle aſpects of the Starres, that ruled either in our conception or birth. Fiftly, want of good nouriſhment. Sixtly, intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance either in our diet, or exerciſe, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying of our affections. To which ſome adde the fewneſſe or tenderneſſe of teeth, for that is a ſigne of thickeneſſe in the bone of the head, the matter allotted to the teeths generation being turned into the ſubſtance of the ſcull, which alſo importeth the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the braine, which is by meanes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:22836:68"/>vnfit for breathing, and therefore being of a moiſt diſpoſition, the more fit for putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as ſtanding-waters ſooneſt putrefie and gather filth: but this I take rather for a ſigne then a cauſe of ſhort life.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Now come we to that we firſt and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally intended, to ſhew the differences of mens ages, and the cauſes thereof, together with their ſeuerall and ſingular properties, wherein we will deale ſo much the more ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly by reaſon of thoſe doubtes and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties remooued in the former part of the treatiſe, ſo that we ſhall not neede to digreſſe into any by-controuerſies but keepe a direct and a ſtraight courſe. And to begin with the <hi>Definition,</hi> (for more orderly proceeding) it may thus briefely be deſcribed: <hi>An age is a period and tearme of mans life, wherein his naturall complexion and temperature naturally and of its owne accord is euidently changed.</hi> For ſuch is the diſpoſition and nature of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, that by the continuall combat and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable dominion of the euer-iarring elements it often changeth its primary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, ſo that though there were no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſe of tranſmutation, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding are many and manifold, yet haue wee that home-bred cauſe within vs that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:22836:69"/>would in time alter our temperature, for our naturall heat vnceſſantly working vpon our natural moiſture doth, though not ſuddenly, change the proportion into extreames, yet by degrees perceiuably preuaileth more and more ouer the humidity. For ſo ſee wee the ſame body in our youth and child-hood, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly tempered, our <hi>infancy</hi> ful of moiſture, as the fluid ſoft ſubſtance of our fleſh mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly declareth: our <hi>youth</hi> bringeth a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther degree of ſolidity: our <hi>riper age</hi> euer te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate: thence ſtill declineth our body vnto colde and drineſſe, till at length death cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vpon our bodies, being the laſt end and period of our life. But euery ſlight change of the foure qualities proportion changeth not our temperature, for then we ſhuld eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day haue a diuers complexion, our bodies eftſoones with wine and exerciſe changed from cold to heat, and by the contrary from heat to cold: yet by reaſon of the ſhort in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durance of theſe diſtemperatures, the body returning to its former conſtitution, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay there is a new complexion wrought in the body: for a temperature or complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is <hi>a firme and ſtanding habit of the body.</hi> Nor yet muſt wee imagine the talneſſe and growing of the body or the new budding of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:22836:69"/>haires, to be cauſes ſufficient to procure this diſtinction; but the variation of our originall conſtitution is the true and proper cauſe of this diuerſity and difference. And yet not euery change of the complexion, but that onely which proceedeth from that inwardly ingendred cauſe of deſtructions; for many times by the vnſeaſonable and immoderate heat of the aire, as alſo by intemperate and riotous liuing, men euen in the moſt milde &amp; temperat countries, alter their complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and with the Aethiopian, become euen decrepit old men (if we reſpect their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and thoſe other incident qualities of old age) before they haue finiſhed the full tearme of thirty yeeres; and therefore was it added in the deſcription, that it muſt be a naturall and a ſelfe-alteration. Now according to theſe naturall and euident alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of heat and moiſtures proportion, ſo may we beſt &amp; moſt properly diuide the ages. <hi>Pythagoras</hi> diuides the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into four kinds, or rather ſetteth downe their number, which be according to his reckoning foure in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>Child-hood, youth, man-hood, old age,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioning our life to the foure parts of the yeere, our <hi>Child-hood</hi> to the <hi>ſpring,</hi> wherein all things together with a pleaſant verdour
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:22836:70"/>and greeneneſſe flouriſh and by a plentifull ſupply of moiſture continually increaſe in growth. Our <hi>youth</hi> vnto <hi>Summer,</hi> for that growen ſtrength of the body and minde. Our <hi>man-age</hi> vnto the <hi>Autumne</hi> or <hi>Harueſt,</hi> when after the manifold turmoiles and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of our fore-ſpent life, the good giftes and indowments of our minde (as we ſee it fall out in the fruites of Nature) receiue a kind of ſeaſonable and timely ripeneſſe. Our <hi>old age</hi> hee reſembleth vnto the colde and troubleſome <hi>winter ſeaſon,</hi> very fitly thereby expreſſing the cumberſome coldneſſe of the latter end of our life. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſetteth downe onely three diſtinct ages, <hi>child-hood, flours<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing man-age,</hi> and <hi>old-age;</hi> the firſt plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abounding with heat and moiſture; the middle age hauing the ſame two qualities of life, aſwell tempered as their nature poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly can be; old age declining and ſwaruing from that good and moderate temper, and by little and little decaying in both theſe qualities, till at length they be both of them conſumed. Now that our life is thus often, and thus in order changed in the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it will eaſily appeare, if we conſider the matter whereof we are all made, and that is <hi>ſemen &amp; ſanguis parentum,</hi> both abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:22836:70"/>with heat and moiſture, whereout ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this conſequence, that in the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into life, wee haue groateſt ſtore of thoſe two liuely qualities, which decay not but by length of time; and that in our infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie wee are fulleſt of moiſture, our experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſenſe teacheth vs, for ſo we ſee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants fleſh moſt fluid and almoſt of a waxen diſpoſition, ready to receiue impreſſion of any light touch; and as for heat, <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> both conſent, that <hi>man is moſt hot in the firſt day of his birth,</hi> though by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great ſtore of moiſture, the heats power doth not ſo euidently appeere: and becauſe the heat without any the leaſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or pauſe, worketh vpon our moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and by little and little conſumeth it, it ſelfe alſo in time decaying, who ſeeth not that the beſt part of our life, euen neceſſarily is moſt cold and drie? whence alſo this may be inferred; that the ſpace between the two extremes, is moſt temperate, foraſmuch as <hi>Nature neuer paſſeth from one extreme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other, but by the meane:</hi> and this is the warrant of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> tripartite diuiſion of ages; the ſeuerals are thus briefly defined.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/>
               <hi>Childhood is the firſt part and age of a mans life, wherein their generation and growth is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected,</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:22836:71"/>and this laſteth (for the moſt part) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till wee be fiue and twentie yeeres old, and this age is proportionable vnto the <hi>Spring,</hi> hot and moiſt, for in this time our naturall heat ſupplieth greater ſtore of vitall aerie moiſture, from the nouriſhment receiued, than was ſpent of that our naturall ſtore; &amp; thence it is, that within compaſſe of this time, our bodies grow bigger and taller. But according to the ſucceſſiue decay and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of our heat and moiſture, it hath pleaſed <hi>antiquitie</hi> to point out certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of this firſt age; the firſt is our infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and that laſteth vntil the third or fourth yeere of our life, and is alwaies beſt ſtored with moiſture: the next is our boy hood, and that laſteth other fiue yeeres: the third our <hi>budding</hi> and <hi>bloſſoming age,</hi> when our cheekes and other more hidden parts begin to be clothed with that moſſie exerement of haire, which is proroged vntill the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeere: the laſt our <hi>youth,</hi> laſting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we be fiue and twentie yeeres old; and theſe are the parts of our growing age. The next is our <hi>flouriſhing</hi> and <hi>middle age,</hi> and this is, when a man is come to the higheſt degree of perfection in the temper of his body, &amp; continueth in that flouriſhing liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:22836:71"/>without any notorious decay or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing his heat, ſupplying the iuſt quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of moiſture from the nouriſhment, which in the former action of it, was conſumed; and this is compared to the <hi>Summer,</hi> hot and drie, or rather moderately moiſt, drie onely in compariſon of the former age, not ſimplie, leſt the heat ſhould too ſoone diſſolue the body; and this alſo hath it parts; the firſt is our <hi>youth,</hi> (for ſo the penurie of our Engliſh toong warranteth me to call it) when our growth is ſtaied, and our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat beginneth to be moſt flouriſhing; you may call it our <hi>Prime,</hi> for then indeed are wee in our prime and moſt flouriſhing eſtate; it laſteth from the fiue and twenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the fiue and thirtieth or fortieth yeere of our life: the ſecond part of our middle age, is our <hi>Manhood,</hi> the moſt conſtant and ſetled part of our life, as hauing our life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualities moſt firme and in greateſt medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie, wherein notwithſtanding our naturall heat beginnes a little to decay and decline from its vigour; yet ſo, as it cannot by ſenſe be perceiued, and this laſteth oftentimes till we be fiftie yeeres old. The laſt is <hi>old age,</hi> when not onely the augmentatiue facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſoule ceaſeth to increaſe the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:22836:72"/>of our bodies, but alſo by reaſon of our heats and moiſtures decay, there is a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt declining from our former luſtineſſe and liuelihood, our bodily ſtrength together with the weake and feeble operations of our ſoule in her functions ſenſiblie impaired. And this laſt part of our life is reſembled vnto <hi>Winter,</hi> for that although it be in it ſelf hot and moiſt, (as life conſiſteth wholly in theſe two qualities) yet in compariſon of the former ages, and in regard of death, vnto which it leadeth vs, is accounted cold, and this hath alſo its degrees or parts: the firſt wherein our ſtrength and heat are euidently impaired, yet not ſo much, but that there remaineth a will and readineſſe to bee do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and this laſteth vſually from our fifti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth yeere vnto our three-ſcore and fiue. The ſecond part of this laſt part of our life, which they call decrepit old age, is when our ſtrength and heat is ſo farre decaied, that not onely all abilitie is taken away, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all willingneſſe, to the leaſt ſtrength and motion of our bodie: and this is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion and end of our life, reſembling death it ſelfe, whoſe harbinger and fore-runner it is: and ſo haue we ſeuen ſeuerall parts of our life, compriſing our <hi>Pubertatem</hi> and <hi>adole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentiam,</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:22836:72"/>vnder one: accordingly whereto the Aſtrologers haue aſſigned to euerie of them their peculiar predominant Planet: our <hi>Infant age</hi> is allotted to the <hi>Moones</hi> milde and moiſt dominion, cheriſhing vs with her ſweet influence which ſhe hath eſpecially vpon moiſt bodies: our <hi>Boy-hood, Mercury</hi> hath charge ouer, inclining vs to <hi>ſportfulneſſe, talke,</hi> and <hi>learning: Venus</hi> guides our bloſſomming <hi>luſtfull age:</hi> our youthfull <hi>prime,</hi> by the <hi>Sunnes</hi> liuely operation is lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp from baſe delights, to a loftier and more man like reſolution and liuelineſſe. <hi>Mars</hi> the ſterne god of warre, hath the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of his dominion limited within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of our man-age, adding courage to our liuelihood, and whetting our otherwiſe dull ſpirits, vnto a more ventrous boldneſſe in quarrelling combats: <hi>Old age</hi> from <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> receiueth granitie and ſtaiedneſſe: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit <hi>crooked age,</hi> from the angrie aſpect of drie <hi>Saturne,</hi> ſucketh the poiſonous infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of craſie ſickneſſe and waiward pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe: and this is briefly the ſummarie explication of the differences of mans ages, and the cauſes of this diſtinction, together with thoſe properties which the Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans myſtically and darkly haue propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:22836:73"/>as proper and peculiar to euery and all of them, to which if we adde the expoſition of ſome few problemes incident to this Treatiſe, wee will preſently annex our Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> The firſt doubt is, <hi>What the reaſon may be of our crying and lamenting at our very firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the world.</hi> There are that attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute this mourning vnto a diuining, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall forefeeling as it were of the calamities to come: but I rather thinke it ariſeth from thoſe infirmities and griefes which wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently feele, aſwell for want of ſome good thing which we deſire, as alſo for ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and greeuance of ſome incumbent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie: as firſt that violent motion from that before ſo quietly inioied bedde (as it were) in the wombe. Secondly the ſtraight nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſſe of that paſſage by which wee enter into the world. Thirdly, the cold and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie intertainment which we haue, driuen out of our warme harbour in the cloſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceiueable habitation of our mothers wombe, and barred of that nouriſhment which we before had vnceſſantly miniſtred vnto vs; and thence is it, that preſently we betake our ſelues to that <hi>dary-houſe</hi> of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, euen by a naturall inſtinct and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:22836:73"/>where when wee haue well battled our ſelues, &amp; by the enwrapping in our clothes, are armed againſt the colde aires iniuries, our begunne lamentations are pacified and turned into a quiet contentedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> Secondly, it may be demanded, <hi>why chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in their ſucking age are naturally more gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto ſleepe, then when they be of more ripe yeeres.</hi> The reaſon is natures mother-like prouidence that for the better ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſpeedier perfection of her of spring, vſeth this as a meanes to increaſe the vertue, and operation of the heat, and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hath ſtored their head with moiſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, fitted through their rarity and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for the braines coole operation vpon them. For as vnited forces are ſtrongeſt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for aſſault or reſiſtance, ſo the ſcattering diſcontinuity of the thin vapours is an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the colds eaſier impreſſion, and ſo of their thickning &amp; better ſtopping of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the ſpirits vnto the outward ſenſes. Another cauſe may be the braines coldneſſe, as hauing in ſo little time receiued no great annoiance from the ſtomacks diſtempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it ſelfe alſo abounding with moiſtuure &amp; fit matter for procuring of ſleepe. Thirdly, the good digeſtion of that mild milkie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:22836:74"/>whence aſcendeth into the head the ſoundeſt and moſt pure exhalations. And therfore are their ſleepes (for the moſt part) without any the leaſt painefulneſſe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation, whereas contrarily we ſee ſurchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſtomackes breed vnquiet ſleepes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> Thirdly, the queſtion may be, <hi>why the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall vitall actions, as nutrition, augmentation, and ſuch like, are in infants ſo powerfull, and thoſe other of ſenſe ſo feeble and vneffectuall.</hi> The anſwer is, that the good performance of thoſe actions of life dependeth principally vpon our naturall heat; For our ſoule, the prince of our body hath aſſigned to our heat the adminiſtration and ordering of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince: no maruell therefore if thoſe duties be well performed in our infancy, when the author of them is at that time moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and plentifull. Now the reaſon of the ſenſes weake operation is the fewneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits deputed to that function: for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall ſpirits of ſenſe being to be made in the ſhop or worke-houſe of the braine by the braine, that excellent ſpirituall artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, the workeman howſoeuer he bee his craftſmaſter, as hauing beene Natures <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice,</hi> yet by reaſon of his imbeeillity and weakeneſſe is not able in ſo ſhort ſpace to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:22836:74"/>make many or at leaſt not ſo forceable inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as may ſerue for the high function &amp; duty of the ſoule. To which we may adde the abundance of moiſture, wherewith the celles of the braine are in our infancy ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowen hindring the actions of the ſoules ſenſitiue parts, and dulling her thereto or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained faculties.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> Where alſo wee haue opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue a fourth doubt, <hi>why children haue ſo ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and ſhort memories.</hi> The reaſon thereof is, their braines too great humidity, whereby it is diſabled to keepe the impreſſions of the outward ſenſes obiects. For there are two eſpeciall annoiances of the braine that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our memoratiue faculties, immoderate drineſſe and too great moiſture. For the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of drought cauſeth exceſſe of hardneſſe to reſiſt the impreſſions. And therefore it is that old men for the moſt part haue ſo bad memories, their naturall moiſture being by the heats long continued operation almoſt waſted. And <hi>Galen</hi> in his treatiſe of the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, failing becauſe of drineſſe,</hi> maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Student,</hi> that through immoderate watching and ſtudiouſneſſe had ſo exceſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dried his braine, that he had almoſt quite loſt his remembrance: as alſo of an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:22836:75"/>that by too much paines in that his painefull vocation, and the ſlenderneſſe of hungry-fare, was in danger of the like for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting inconuenience. And as drineſſe by not admitting the impreſſion, is an impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the memory, ſo is alſo too much moiſture by not preſeruing the imprinted <hi>ſpecies.</hi> For ſo ſee we water howſoeuer moſt yeelding, yet leaſt fit to retaine any figure imprinted. Children therefore ſo moiſt brai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned muſt needes be ſhort remembranced.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> The next queſtion is, <hi>Whether ſpeech be naturall or wholly from diſcipline.</hi> The anſwer is, that it is naturall, as vertue and other good habits be, nature hauing giuen a diſpoſition and fitneſſe, together with inſtruments fit for that purpoſe. But as wax howſoeuer capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any impreſſion by reaſon of its plia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature, yet without the putting to of ſome outward ſeale, hath no actuall print or reſemblance of any thing; ſo our nature, though as fit to receiue any thing taught as wax is to receiue impreſſion from the ſeale, yet without the helpe of ſome outward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer, is not actually and fully indowed with any how proper ſo euer a quality, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as are auailable for knowledge. In the which kind this of ſpeech hath a ſpeciall
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:22836:75"/>prerogatiue; but leſt I ſhould ſeeme to bee needleſſely buſied in this queſtion, I referre the Reader for his farther ſatisfaction to that excellent French Poet <hi>Du Bartas,</hi> in his Babylon, Engliſhed by maſter <hi>William L'iſle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> A ſixt queſtion is, <hi>Why children in their infancie haue no actuall euident vſe of their reaſon.</hi> The cauſe is, the abundance of moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture incident to that age, whereby the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the inward ſenſes as with a cloud are either obſcured, or els quite hindred: whence was that forementioned ſpeech of the learned <hi>Plato, That there is a little mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of folly and moiſture in men:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Galen</hi> was woont to ſay, that <hi>flegme</hi> the moſt wateriſh <hi>of all bumors, was little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profitable for the attainment of learning.</hi> In the ſeuenth place it is demanded, why <hi>children moſt fretfull are vſually ſhorteſt liued?</hi> the reaſon is, their plentie of heat in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of their ſmall ſtore of moiſture; for therfore are cholericke complexioned men moſt pettiſh, becauſe their blood is by the fiery heat of that humor ſo ſoone inflamed: wherupon the Egyptians auouched the <hi>Fly</hi> to be the <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> of <hi>anger,</hi> and <hi>perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie,</hi> becauſe (as <hi>Pierius</hi> obſerueth) it is of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:22836:76"/>ſo cholericke and fierie a diſpoſition, and we ſee in experience, men in anger fiery co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured, which proceeds from their heats in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flaming of the blood. Now heat vnpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned vnto the moiſture (as is aforeſaid) quickly conſumeth that ſmall ſtore of moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture prouided for its food and ſo procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth death.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> To theſe may be added that welknowen Probleme of <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> why <hi>children breath faſter and with leſſe intermiſſion then doe better growen men.</hi> The anſwer is, their great ſtore of heat in compariſon of that ſmall meaſure in the after-ages, cauſeth nature for its bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preſeruation, to draw the aire oftner for the cooling of the hearts heat: and that is the reaſon that men who haue beene anie long time troubled with an <hi>ague,</hi> or any ſuch like diſtemperature, are alwaies verie ſhort winded: The contrary <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> witneſſeth to follow, in things contrarily affected, for ſo he prooneth the <hi>horſe</hi> and <hi>exe</hi> not to haue ſo much heat in them; becauſe they take not their breath ſo thicke together; imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the cold temper of the heart and other inwards, is cauſe of longer breath; which is alſo euident in reaſon, for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction and emiſſion of the aire being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:22836:76"/>onely for the cooling and tempring of the harts heat, according to the neceſſity thereof, muſt breathing be either oftner or more ſeldome. <hi>What is the reaſon that in our youth we are more hungrie, and haue a greater deſire of meat, than in our declining and elder ages?</hi> The reaſon is, our ſound &amp; ſpeedy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of fore receiued nouriſhment per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by meanes of our naturall heat, whence ariſeth a new ſucking of the veines, and ſo an incitement of the appetite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whence is it that old men are commonly ſo iealouſly ſuſpicious?</hi> The cauſe is their incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity &amp; hardneſſe of beliefe, which it ſelfe alſo proceedeth from their much experience of mens wilie practiſes, according to that, <hi>The burnt child dreadeth the fire.</hi> For ſuch is the extreme badneſſe of our nature, that ſtill we go from one extreme vnto another; &amp; ſo become of men extremely credulous, in our laſt age extremely ſuſpicious. And that indeed was <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> remedie, who <hi>to draw vs from conetouſneſſe, biddes vs incline vnto prodigalitie:</hi> and yet onely with this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if we cannot at the firſt inſtant after our long cuſtome in the one extreme, light vpon the mediocritie betweene both. <hi>What maketh them ſo ſottiſhly deuoted to the things
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:22836:77"/>of this world; that when they are neerest vnto death, they are moſt deſirous not only to keepe that which before they had gotten, but more &amp; more to increaſe their ſtore?</hi> The reaſon is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Rhetoricks: and it is their exceeding great deſire of life, euen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe many daies which they haue fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce proceedeth that other inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deſire of things neceſſary for life-main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, they hauing in their experience ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued how hardly things neceſſary are got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, how eaſily alſo they are loſt. What is the cauſe, why <hi>old men are ſo talkatiue and full of words?</hi> Either becauſe nature loues to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe that part moſt which is leaſt decaied: or that knowledge, the onely thing old age can bragge of, cannot be manifeſted but by vtterance: or that old men, the nigher they are to their end, they much more deſire to haue their memory not onely by children and poſterity, but euen by the ſpeeches and deedes fore-vttered and performed in their life: or that wiſedome (as all good things naturally communicate their good proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) makes them deſirous to profit others.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/>
               <hi>Whence is that froſty horineſſe that vſually lighteth vpon mens heads in the winter and cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt age of their life?</hi> There are ſome, that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:22836:77"/>it to proceed from the drineſſe of thoſe excrements: which alſo they goe about to prooue by the like experiment in bones, which after their humour is drawen out by ſeething, grow more and more white, till at length they come vnto a perfect and full whiteneſſe. But the vntrue reſolution of the doubt propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, is therby diſcouered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that men who vſe to couer their haire, are ſoner gray-headed than thoſe that vſe no couering, when as notwithſtanding it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that couered haire hath more ſtore of moiſture than that which hath beene expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto the iniurious toſſing of the winde, and the ſcorching heat of the ſunne. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I rather allow of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> reaſon, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the put refaction of that excrementall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, whereof our haire is made: for our naturall heat through its vnintermitted ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, being diſabled fully to digeſt that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement ſent from within to that outmoſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, our skin, for the haires nouriſhment, it putrefieth and corrupteth. Now that there is ſuch a rottenneſſe and putrefaction in the haire, it is euident by experience of ſuch as by long ſickeneſſe haue become vntimely grayheaded: for after the recouery of their diſeaſe the feebleneſſe of their heate being
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:22836:78"/>together with their health reſtored, the haire receiues its former flouriſhing and (that I may ſo ſpeake (vnwaſted greeneneſſe, which reſtitution can be attributed vnto no other cauſe but only to the through conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that vndigeſted excrement by the reſtored heat. The like whereof we ſee alſo in corne and graſſe, that hauing loſt its flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing greeneneſſe, by the continuall beating vpon and ouerwhelming of the waters, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward being by the Sunnes liuely heat cheriſhed and reuiued, reſumeth its naturall vigour and viridity. And that this hoari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headedneſſe proceeds from a defect of heat, it is farther euidenced by a ſtrange example recorded by <hi>Scaliger,</hi> of a man who in one nights ſpace had his head ouergrowen with hoarineſſe. The cauſe was this. The Prince of <hi>Mantoua, Francis Gonzaga,</hi> had vpon ſuſpicion of traiterous conſpiracy, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſon or ſtate, impriſoned one of his kin &amp; alliance that for his age was wholy vncapable of that alteration: and vpon the next morrow newes was brought vnto the Prince that his head was all vpon the ſudden growen hoarily gray; which almoſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous alteration mooued the Princes minde to grant him life and free vſe of his former li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:22836:78"/>Now if any man ſhould demand the reaſon of this ſudden change, it is giuen by the Philoſophers, and is nothing elſe but the extremity of his griefe and feare, whence proceeded that withdrawing of the diſperſed heat vnto the inward parts, and ſo was the humorous nouriſhment of the haire for want of concoction turned into rottenneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> And thus haue we briefly runne ouer the diuerſities of mans ages together with the true cauſes and properties of the particulars, hauing premiſed the determination of thoſe vſually incident controuerſies for our better and more direct proceeding in the principall treatiſe: not as <hi>Prolegomena</hi> or preface to the purpoſe, but as things eſſentiall and of the ſubſtance of our matter. Wherein if I haue either omitted any thing pertinent, or admitted ought that is ſuperfluous, I hope, the <hi>eie of fauour</hi> wil wincke at my miſſing; as for the <hi>malicious,</hi> ſeeing I cannot looke for fauourable acceptance, I weigh not their verdict: onely as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Equitem mihi plaudere curo:</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>The baſer ſort I care to pleaſe no more;</l>
                  <l>One if I pleaſe, enough is me therefore.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
